<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="./examples.xml">
<properties>
<author>Mike Schachter</author>
<author>Ted Husted</author>
<author>James Holmes</author>
<title>Resources - Projects and Examples - Jakarta Struts</title>
</properties>
<body> 
<chapter name="Struts Resources"> 

<section name="Projects and Examples">

<p><a href="http://www.ibatis.com/jpetstore/jpetstore.html"><strong>JPetStore 3</strong></a> by Clinton Begin - A new JPetStore has arrived! Version 3 takes the best of the previous implementations and puts them together into one comprehensive example of web application architecture using Struts, Data Access Objects and advanced JDBC (via SQL Maps)..</p>
<p><a href="http://www.codeczar.com/products/logweb/index.html"><strong>LogWeb</strong></a> by Nathan Coast - A Struts webapp for configuring Log4J at runtime within a servlet container.</p>
<p><a href="http://raibledesigns.com/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=StrutsResume"><strong>Struts Resume</strong></a> by Matt Raible - A resume hosting application built using AppFuse.</p>
<p><a href="http://raibledesigns.com/wiki/Wiki.jsp?page=AppFuse"><strong>AppFuse</strong></a> by Matt Raible - Demonstrates how to use XDoclet with Struts to generate your Forms, web.xml, struts-config.xml, and validation.xml. AppFuse also shows how you can use the different security packages (i.e. form-based authentication, SSLExt) and advanced Struts techniques (i.e. Tiles, Validator) to build your webapps. AppFuse integrates with Hibernate on the backend to do database persistence.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.reumann.net/do/struts/main"><strong>Struttin' with Struts</strong></a> by Rick Reumann - How to use iBATIS Database Layer with Struts, lessons and examples.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ajug.org/meetings/download/struts_demo.zip"><strong>AJUG Presentation Demo Application</strong></a> by Chuck Cavaness - The demo application uses OJB and Hypersonic.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.ehatchersolutions.com/JavaDevWithAnt/"><strong>JavaDevWithAnt</strong></a> by Erik Hatchter - Demonstrates using Ant, XDoclet, Struts, JUnit, Cactus, and Lucene within the same application.</p>
<p><a href="http://basicportal.sourceforge.net/"><strong>basicPortal</strong></a> by Vic Cekvenich - Sample Struts + JSTL Vertical apps</p>
<p><a href="http://chiki.emaho.org/"><strong>Chiki</strong></a> by GhootEmaho - A Wiki-like webapp built using Struts and J2EE,  and runs on Tomcat.</p>
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=49385"><strong>Artimus</strong></a> by Ted  Husted - News poster application. Demonstrates using beans beans and a JDBC database with Struts, along with other niceties. WAR zipped for download. Uses Scaffold package. See WEB-INF/README.txt for setup.</p>
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=49385"><strong>Scaffold</strong></a> by Ted Husted - Utility package of classes that can be used with various Web applications.</p>
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=49385"><strong>Struts Polls</strong></a> by Ted Husted - Simple poll application. Demonstrates using a database with Struts.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.newparticles.com/struts/"><strong>The Struts Framework</strong></a> by Steve Wilkinson - Excerpt from latest Wrox Professional JSP book.</p>
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=49385"><strong>Struts Login</strong></a> (WAR file zipped for download) by Ted Husted - A minimalist Struts application demonstrating form validation and tracking users with a session attribute (WAR file).</p>
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=49385"><strong>Struts-Simple</strong></a> by Ted Husted - (WAR file zipped for download) A simple skeleton application outlining the files needs to input and re-display data. Now also demonstrates using &quot;wizards&quot; and &quot;nested&quot; beans.</p>
<p><a href="http://gallery.bluestone.com/scripts/SaISAPI.dll/Gallery.class/demos/i18n/index.jsp"><strong>Sonic Struts Storefront</strong></a><strong> -</strong> The Sonic Struts Storefront sample application demonstrates how to assemble                            an internationalized e-business application using the Struts framework.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.keyboardmonkey.com/StrutMonkey/MonkeyStruts_v2.jsp"><strong>MonkeyStruts</strong></a> by Arron Bates - Running example of nested hierarchy and the Nested Tags (click <a href="http://www.keyboardmonkey.com/downloads/files/examples/StrutMonkey.war">here</a> to download the war. Needs Struts runtime library etc).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.keyboardmonkey.com/downloads/files/tutorials/next_two/nested-tutorial.war"><strong>Nested Tutorial</strong></a> by Arron Bates - War file result of the nested tutorial (requires Struts runtime files).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.keyboardmonkey.com/downloads/files/tutorials/tree_two/monkey-tree.war"><strong>Tree (dynamic nested fun)</strong></a> by Arron Bates - War file result of the tree tutorial (requires Struts runtime files). I never thought I'd ever see, something as funky as a tree... </p>
<p><a href="http://www.ninsky.com/struts/"><strong>Struts Examples</strong></a> by Steve Raeburn - A collection of examples demonstrating commonly used Struts features.</p>
</section>

</chapter></body></document>
