<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="./extensions.xml">
<properties>
<author>Mike Schachter</author>
<author>Ted Husted</author>
<author>James Holmes</author>
<title>Resources - Contributor Extensions - Jakarta Struts</title>
</properties>
<body>
<chapter name="Struts Resources" href="http://husted.com/struts/resources">
<!--
<p><a href=""></a> by . </p>
-->
<section name="Contributor Extensions">
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/imagebuttonbean/"><b>ImageButtonBeanManager</b></a> by Ken Fitzpatrick. Combines the HTML Image Tag and the ImageButtonBean class in a manner analgous to the Struts HTML Submit Tag.</p>
<p><a href="http://dynclass.sourceforge.net/"><b>dynclass.sourceforge.net</b></a> by John Raley. A Class-creation API with very simple but powerful Map-to-JavaBeans translation</p>
<p><a href="http://www.livinglogic.de/Struts/"><b>Workflow Extension</b></a> by Matthias Bauer - An extension to the core Struts framework which provides control flow between actions.</p>
<p><a href="http://otn.oracle.com/products/jdev/content.html">JDeveloper9i 9.0.3 w/ Struts, J2EE 1.3, et. al.</a> by Oracle. Developer's Preview of interest to Struts users who might be using (or might want to evaluate) Oracle's JDeveloper Java IDE</p>
<p><a href="http://jcorporate.com/"><b>Expresso 5.0</b></a> by jCorporate - Expresso provides a foundation set of reusable, standards-based Java software components designed to shorten time-to-delivery of Web applications, and is integrated with the Struts framework. See also <a href="http://www.xenonsoft.demon.co.uk/products/java.html">Best Practice with Expresso Framework 4.0</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.asqdotcom.be/struts/"><b>Struts Action Plug-in Extension 1.0 (for Struts 1.1b)</b></a> by ASQ dot COM. Provides a clean and transparent way to plug-in common controller logic (such as authentication, workflow, etc.) for all Struts actions in an application</p>
<p><a href="http://struts.ditlinger.com/"><b>SSL Ext</b></a> by eBuilt, Inc.<b> </b>- Switch between using the http &amp; https protocols on a page by page basis. See README.txt.</p>
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/htmltable/"><b>HTMLTable framework for Struts framework</b></a> by Yuriy Zubarev - Incorporate look and feel and behaviour (in terms of columns order) of tables in XML configuration file with capabilities of properties inheritance. </p>
<p><a href="http://netmeme.org/simper/"><b>Simper</b></a>  by Bryan Field-Elliot - A simple persistence mechanism - wraps up table rows as &quot;Dynabeans&quot; (see <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-commons/nightly/commons-beanutils/">Jakarta Commons BeanUtils, nightly build</a>), automatically detects changes, and writes the changes back to the database upon completion of each web request; supports creating, deleting rows, querying; basic relations (1-1 and 1-m). </p>
<p><a href="http://webAppWriter.com"><b>webAppWriter </b></a>by dataFundamentals - A Struts application that generates code for Struts applications a/la Expresso.</p>
<p><a href="http://strutstestcase.sourceforge.net/"><b>StrutsTestCase for JUnit</b></a>  by Deryl Seal - An extension of the standard JUnit TestCase class that provides facilities for testing code based on the Struts framework.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.inigoserrano.com/ISValidator/en/ejemploStrutsCompleto0010ISValidator.htm"><b>ISValidator</b></a>  by Inigo Serrano - Validates data in differents scenarios, command line arguements, Servlets Parameters, et cetera. Includes example using theLogonForm from the example application. </p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/checker.html"><b>StrutsResourcesChecker</b></a>  by David White - Parses struts JSP files and looks for those tags which make reference to the application properties file. </p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/pow2acl.htm"><b>Pow2ACL</b></a>  by Luca Fossato - Access Control List library. Track of application users roles and                          permissions. User can be authenticated: - directly using the package API - using custom JSP tag libraries. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.mycgiserver.com/~eboudrant/#rose"><b>Struts .. in Rose</b></a> by Emmanuel.Boudrant - Use Struts with the Rational Rose UML model. </p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/multi-struts.htm"><b>Multi-Controller</b></a> by Sukachevin, Stoehr - Use more than once ActionServlet in your Struts application </p>
<p><a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-user@jakarta.apache.org/msg16093.html"><b>JavaScript with html:errors - new Struts validation</b></a> by Adam Grohs.  </p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/DynamicProperties.htm"><b>Dynamic ActionForm Properties</b></a> by Jan Sorensen.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/bean-util.htm"><b>Bean Utils with Indexed Strings</b></a> by Gregor Rayman.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/struts-security.htm"><b>Role-Based Actions</b></a> by Nic Hobs. Set a security role for an Action from with struts-config.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/ValueIterator.zip"><b>ValueIterator</b></a> by Ted Husted - Simple wrapper around a RowSet for use with Struts iterator tag. Also includes generic toMap(), set(map) methods for flexible data transfer.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.rpsenterprises.com/struts/index.html"><b>Struts Transformer</b></a> by Ron Smith - Transformations are responsible for taking an object in one form and transforming it into another.(e.g. Date object to String;  String to Date).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.rpsenterprises.com/struts/index.html"><b>Struts Extender</b></a> by Ron Smith - Add extensions to the struts framework via entries in the Struts configuration file.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/mapper.htm"><b>Mapper Framework</b></a> by Capco - The Mapper framework can be used for automating the process of validating/converting/transferring data fields. <font size="2">(See README to get started. Updated 18-JUL-2001.)</font></p>
<p><a href="http://www.sura.ru/~gonza/bean-factory/"><b>Bean factory</b></a> by Oleg V Alexeev - Adds the ability to easily link data bean creation to any Struts Action. All information about databeans and actions mappings stored in the standard Struts configuraton file. </p>
<p><a href="http://home.earthlink.net/~dwinterfeldt/"><b>Struts Validator</b></a> [Now bundled with Struts 1.1] by David Winterfeldt - Perform basic validations to check if a field is required, matches a regular expression, and some basic type checking. Different validation rules can be defined for different locales. The framework has basic support for user defined constants which can be used in some field attributes. The validation routines are modifiable in the validation.xml file so custom validation routines can be created and added to the framework.</p>
</section>

</chapter></body></document>
