<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="./guis.xml">
<properties>
<author>Mike Schachter</author>
<author>Ted Husted</author>
<author>James Holmes</author>
<title>Resources - Code Generators and GUIs - Jakarta Struts</title>
</properties>
<body> 
<chapter name="Struts Resources" href="http://husted.com/struts/resources"> 

<section name="Code Generators and GUIs">
<p><a href="http://www.alien-factory.co.uk/struts/struts-index.html"><b>Struts GUI</b></a> by Alien-Factory - Alien-Factory's Struts GUI for Microsoft Visio is essentially a Visio Stencil with Visual Basic Macros.</p>
<p><a href="http://rivernorth.sourceforge.net"><b>Struts Builder</b></a> by RiverNorth - an Opensource tool (GPL license) originally developed for internal use to aid in development of Struts-based web applications (1.1 style).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.synthis.com/products/adalon/overview.jsp"><b>Adalon</b></a> - Adalon is a next generation functional design tool that fills the gaps left by today's market leading software design products. </p>
<p><a href="http://easystruts.sourceforge.net/"><b>Easy Struts Project</b></a> by Emmanuel Boudrant - The aim of this project is to provide a bunch of development tools, for Eclispe v2.0 and Borland JBuilder 5-6, in order to facilitate the development of a web project based on the MVC2 Jakarta Struts framework.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.solanasoft.com"><b>JForms:</b></a> a visual tool for Struts-based Web forms.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/StrutsGen.htm"><b>Struts Gen</b></a> by Cyberzombie - A rudimentary wrapper tool for value objects.</p>
<p><a href="http://xsltgenerator.sourceforge.net/"><b>Struts XSLT Code Generator</b></a> by Shengmeng Liu - An XSLT based code generator for Struts, completely based on the XSLT transformation and a set of stylesheet files. Ideally, users can customize the stylesheet for each type of Struts files  to have templates of their own without having to access the source code and recompile it.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.objectventure.com/products/objectassembler.html"><b>ObjectAssembler</b></a> by ObjectVentur - supports the development of Struts applications, a popular open source web application framework that is part of Apache's Jakarta Project. The same visual development and code synchronization available with J2EE components are available for Struts components.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.objectwave.com/html/tools/tool1_3.htm"><b>X2J</b></a>  by Objectwave - A code generation tool for building Struts applications. It includes wizard for easily creating JSPs, and the required Action and ActionForm classes as well as graphical tools for updating the config file. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/"><b>Struts Console</b></a> by James Holmes. The Struts Console is a standalone Java Swing application for managing Struts-based applications, including plugin support for Sun Forte for Java, NetBeans, Borland JBuilder, and Oracle JDeveloper 9i. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.scioworks.com/scioworks_camino.html"><b>Scioworks Camino</b></a> by Scioworks Pte Ltd. - A visual tool for Struts. </p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/codemaker.htm"><b>Struts CodeMaker</b></a> by Ravindran Ramaiah - Generate Struts application by reading configuration file or JSP files. Updated 2001-08-21.</p>
<p><a href="http://home.earthlink.net/~dwinterfeldt/generator/"><b>Struts Generator</b></a> by David Winterfeldt - Based on the generator.xml and a table/query an xml file is generated.  Based on the generated xml file a primary key class, data bean class, jdbc class, and an ActionForm (Struts) can be generated.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/tldtovlm.zip"><b>TLD to VLM</b></a> by Mario Busche - Simple Java program to convert standard TLD's to the VLM format used by Homesite, CF Studio, and JRun Studio.</p>
<p><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/taglibs/doc/ultradev4-doc/intro.html"><b>UltraDev 4.0 Custom Tag Library Extension</b></a> - Hosted by Jakarta Taglibs.</p>
</section>

</chapter></body></document>
