<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="./guis.xml">
<properties>
<author>Mike Schachter</author>
<author>Ted Husted</author>
<author>James Holmes</author>
<title>Resources - Tools: IDEs, GUIs, and Code Generators - Jakarta Struts</title>
</properties>
<body> 
<chapter name="Struts Resources" href="http://husted.com/struts/resources"> 

<section name="Integrated Development Environments">
<p><a href="http://www.synthis.com/products/adalon/overview.jsp"><b>Adalon</b></a> - Adalon is a next generation functional design tool that fills the gaps left by today's market leading software design products. </p>
<p>Struts Tools in <b><a href="http://www.ibm.com/software/ad/">IBM WebSphere
Studio</a></b> - A full-featured environment for rapid Struts application
development, providing specialized and graphical editors, viewers, and wizards
enabling you to build and manipulate Struts artifacts including JSPs, Java
classes, configuration files and mappings, even entire projects, with
Struts-specific validation.</p>
</section>

<section name="IDE Plugins (Eclipse)">
<p><a href="http://www.strecl.com/">STRECL</a> - A set of tools offering easier utilization of Struts framework, two-way editing of XML files, code generation using wizards (JDBC DAO), JSP editor and many other functions. Oct 16: JSP editor (beta version) is released.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.improve-technologies.com/alpha/struts-config-editor/">Improve Struts Configuration File Editor</a> - struts-config graphical view</p>
<p><a href="http://easystruts.sourceforge.net/"><b>Easy Struts</b></a> by Emmanuel Boudrant - The aim of this project is to provide a bunch of development tools, for Eclipse v2.0 and Borland JBuilder 5-7, in order to facilitate the development of a Struts application. A GUI editor for struts-config.xml files is available in Eclipse 2.0 plugin.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/"><b>Struts Console 3.0</b></a> by James Holmes. The Struts Console is a standalone Java Swing application for managing Struts-based applications, including plugin support for Sun Forte for Java, NetBeans, Borland JBuilder, and Oracle JDeveloper 9i. </p>
<p><a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/tinman">Tinman Project:</a> Essential Java Documentation</p>
<p><a href="http://www.sysdeo.com/eclipse/tomcatPlugin.html">Tomcat Launcher Plugin</a> by Sysdeo</p>	
<p><a href="http://eclipse-plugins.2y.net/eclipse/">More plugins for Eclipse ...</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.metanology.com/MDEforStruts.html"><b>MDE for Struts</b></a> - MDE for Struts is an Eclipse-based IDE that lets you graphically develop Struts 1.1 applications using industry standard UML.</p>
</section>

<section name="IDE Plugins (other)">
<p><a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/"><b>Struts Console 3.0</b></a> by James Holmes. The Struts Console is a standalone Java Swing application for managing Struts-based applications, including plugin support for Sun Forte for Java, NetBeans, Borland JBuilder, and Oracle JDeveloper 9i. </p>
<p><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/taglibs/doc/ultradev4-doc/intro.html"><b>UltraDev 4.0 Custom Tag Library Extension</b></a> - Hosted by Jakarta Taglibs.</p>
</section>

<section name="Visual Tools (GUIs)">
<p><a href="http://www.objectventure.com/products/objectassembler.html"><b>ObjectAssembler 2.5 Pro</b></a> by ObjectVentur - supports the development of Struts applications, a popular open source web application framework that is part of Apache's Jakarta Project. The same visual development and code synchronization available with J2EE components are available for Struts components.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/"><b>Struts Console 3.0</b></a> by James Holmes. The Struts Console is a standalone Java Swing application for managing Struts-based applications, including plugin support for Sun Forte for Java, NetBeans, Borland JBuilder, and Oracle JDeveloper 9i. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.solanasoft.com"><b>JForms:</b></a> a visual tool for Struts-based Web forms.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.scioworks.com/scioworks_camino.html"><b>Scioworks Camino</b></a> by Scioworks Pte Ltd. - A visual tool for Struts. </p>
<p><a href="http://rivernorth.sourceforge.net"><b>Struts Builder</b></a> by RiverNorth - an Opensource tool (GPL license) originally developed for internal use to aid in development of Struts-based web applications (1.1 style).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.alien-factory.co.uk/strutsgui/"><b>Struts GUI</b></a> by Alien-Factory - Alien-Factory's Struts GUI for Microsoft Visio is essentially a Visio Stencil with Visual Basic Macros.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.exadel.com/products_strutsstudio.htm"><b>Struts Studio</b></a> by Exadel Inc. - A visual drag-and-connect approach to rapid development of Struts web applications.</p>
</section>
	
<section name="Code Generators">
<p><a href="http://www.javanovic.com"><b>Karapan Sapi:</b></a> open source generator software for the Struts framework.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/codemaker.htm"><b>Struts CodeMaker</b></a> by Ravindran Ramaiah - Generate Struts application by reading configuration file or JSP files. Updated 2001-08-21.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/StrutsGen.htm"><b>Struts Gen</b></a> by Cyberzombie - A rudimentary wrapper tool for value objects.</p>
<p><a href="http://home.earthlink.net/~dwinterfeldt/generator/"><b>Struts Generator</b></a> by David Winterfeldt - Based on the generator.xml and a table/query an xml file is generated.  Based on the generated xml file a primary key class, data bean class, jdbc class, and an ActionForm (Struts) can be generated.</p>
<p><a href="http://xsltgenerator.sourceforge.net/"><b>Struts XSLT Code Generator</b></a> by Shengmeng Liu - An XSLT based code generator for Struts, completely based on the XSLT transformation and a set of stylesheet files. Ideally, users can customize the stylesheet for each type of Struts files  to have templates of their own without having to access the source code and recompile it.</p>
<p><a href="http://husted.com/struts/resources/tldtovlm.zip"><b>TLD to VLM</b></a> by Mario Busche - Simple Java program to convert standard TLD's to the VLM format used by Homesite, CF Studio, and JRun Studio.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.objectwave.com/html/tools/tool1_3.htm"><b>X2J</b></a>  by Objectwave - A code generation tool for building Struts applications. It includes wizard for easily creating JSPs, and the required Action and ActionForm classes as well as graphical tools for updating the config file. </p>
</section>

</chapter></body></document>
