<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="./utilities.xml">
<properties>
<author>Mike Schachter</author>
<author>Ted Husted</author>
<author>James Holmes</author>
<title>Resources - Other Struts-Related Utilities - Jakarta Struts</title>
</properties>
<body> 
<chapter name="Struts Resources"> 

<section name="Other Struts-Related Tools and Utilities">

    <p>
        <a href="http://displaytag.sourceforge.net/"><strong>The display tag library</strong></a> is an open source
        suite of custom tags that provide high level web presentation patterns which will work in a MVC model,
        and provide a significant amount of functionality while still being simple and straight-forward to use.
    </p>

    <p>
        <a href="http://fitnesse.org"><strong>Fitnesse</strong></a>The fully integrated standalone wiki, and acceptance
        testing framework.
    </p>

    <p>
        <a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/"><strong>Faces Console</strong></a> by James Holmes.
        The Faces Console is a FREE standalone Java Swing application for managing JavaServer Faces-based
        applications. With the Faces Console you can visually edit JavaServer Faces configuration files as well as
        JSP Tag Library files.
    </p>

    <p>
        <a href="http://wwws.sun.com/software/products/projectrave/">Project Rave</a> - a new generation tool for Java
        application development (early release).
    </p>

    <p>
        <a href="http://www.jplates.com/">JPlates</a> produces standards-based software tools that dramatically improve
        productivity for all template-based applications, including Struts JSP/Velocity/XLST applications.
    </p>

    <p>
        <a href="http://ultrawork.org/wtk/index.html"><strong>Web Toolkit</strong></a> - provides a component-based
        approach to building markup-driven applications (not Struts specific). Alternative to the Template and Tiles
        taglibs.
    </p>

    <p>
        <a href="http://jdbforms.sourceforge.net/"><strong>dbForms</strong></a> - RAD framework for database
        applications.
    </p>

    <p>
        <a href="http://jsptags.com/tags/navigation/pager/"><strong>Pager Tag Library</strong></a> - helps generate
        Google and AltaVista style search result navigators. It will take multiple pages worth of information,
        dynamically split it up into page sized pieces and generate a browsable index. It does this in a flexible way
        that allows designers to give the index just about any look desired.
    </p>

</section>

</chapter></body></document>
