<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document url="./ssl.xml">

<properties>

<author>James Mitchell</author>

<title>How to setup struts in Netbeans IDE - Apache Struts</title>

</properties>

<body>

<chapter href="netbeans" name="How to setup struts in Netbeans IDE">
	
<section name="For working on the distribution itself">
<ol>
<li>
 Create a new project (from the Project Manager window)
</li>
<li>
 Download the struts source distribution (or use built-in cvs to get
 the module)
</li>
<li>
 Extract to a local drive (if on windoze, try not to have spaces in
 the directory (such as C:\My Documents)
</li>
<li>
 Mount the directory you unzipped to
</li>
<li>
 Copy build.properties.sample to build.properties and customize to point
 to where you keep those jars
</li>
<li>
 Mount each of the source directories that you wish to work in
 For me, I use:<br />
 <code>
    jakarta-struts/src/share<br />
    jakarta-struts/src/example
  </code>
</li>
<li>
 Mount each jar referenced in the build.properties file<br />
 <b>Note</b> - NetBeans has built in support for auto-mounting these if your
 build.xml specifies the jars in the project.classpath, but
 that's not the case for the default struts distribution.
</li>
</ol>
</section>
	
<section name="For doing your own thing">
<ol>
<li>
 Create a new project (from the Project Manager window)
</li>
<li>
 Download (or build for yourself) the required jars<br />
 (See the jakarta-struts-1.1-b2/webapps/struts-example.war)
</li>
<li>
  Create a directory (I use a structure similar to how the webapp will exist)
<pre>
   +-/my-project
     |
     +-/WEB-INF
       |
       +-/classes
       |
       +-/lib
       |
       +-/src</pre>
</li>
<li>
 Create a build.xml for your project (so ant can build and war it for you).
 I recommend you use an existing file to get a jump start on development.
 Actually, I recommend you re-use someone's entire existing project.  That
 will surely get you ahead of the game.
</li>
<li>
 Mount that directory<br />
 <i>If you specified the build classpath and the jars are there, NetBeans 
 will mount the jars for you automatically.</i>
</li>
<li>
 Mount each of the source directories that you wish to work in
 /myproject/WEB-INF/src
</li>
<li>
 Always work in the node in #6 when modifying your java files.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
I'll also take this opportunity to tell you that I recommend using Eclipse.  I
was a NetBeans advocate for the longest time, but a few weeks ago several
discussion had prompted me to try out Eclipse, and I can say without a doubt,
that it is much more mature an IDE than NetBeans.  And since they are both Open
Source.....hey....why not?
</p>
<p>
One definite advantage Eclipse has over NetBeans is that Eclipse is built using
SWT (Standard Widget Toolkit).  That means that the IDE is written in Java, but
the underlying framework uses native JNDI calls the OS API.....or, in other
words......"its fast as Hell on windows".
</p>
<p>
Anyone who has left NetBeans running in the background overnight on a laptop
knows the pain of doing an Alt+Tab back to the IDE and seeing how Swing pulls
its rather large A## up from the swap file....heh heh :)
</p>
<p>
Hope that will help you get started.  I was planning to post a how-to for doing
this and a few other tasks with NetBeans, Eclipse, and JBuilder.  I even have
quite a few screenshots taken, but I just haven't finished it.
</p>
<p>
Good Luck with it!!!
</p>

</section>

</chapter></body></document>
