<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./index.xml">

  <properties>
    <author>Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author>Ted Husted</author>
    <author>Martin Cooper</author>
    <title>The Struts Framework Project</title>
  </properties>

  <body>


  <section name="Welcome to Struts" href="Welcome">

  <p>
  Welcome to the Struts Framework!  The goal of this project
  is to provide an open source framework for building Web applications 
  that integrates standard technologies like 
  <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet"> Java Servlets</a>, 
  <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/">JavaBeans</a>, 
  and <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp">JavaServer 
  Pages</a> (JSP). 
  </p>
  <p>
  Struts encourages application architectures based the
  <b>Model-View-Controller</b> (MVC) design paradigm, colloquially known as
  <i>Model 2</i> in discussions on various Java mailing lists. Struts 
  provides its own <b>Controller</b> component and integrates 
  with other technologies to provide the Model and the View. 
  For the <b>Model</b>, Struts can interact with any standard data 
  access technology, including 
  <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/ejb/index.html">
  Enterprise Java Beans</a>, 
  <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jdbc/index.html"> 
  JDBC</a>, and 
  <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jndi/index.html"> 
  JNDI</a>. 
  For the <b>View</b>, Struts works well with 
  <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp">JavaServer 
  Pages</a>, 
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/index.html">
  Velocity Templates</a>, 
  XSLT, and 
  <a href="resources.html#views">
  other presentation systems
  </a>.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Struts framework provides the invisible underpinnings every 
  professional Web application needs to survive. Struts helps you 
  create an extensible development environment for your application, 
  based on published standards and proven design patterns.
  </p>

  <p>
  Struts is part of the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">Jakarta
  Project</a>, sponsored by the
  <a href="http://www.apache.org">Apache Software Foundation</a>.  The
  official Struts home page is at
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts">http://jakarta.apache.org/struts</a>.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Learning About Struts" href="Docs">

  <blockquote>
  Note: Most of the links in this section refer to the <b>Nightly Build</b>. 
  When learning about Struts, <b>be sure to refer to the documentation for the 
  version you are actually using</b>. The documentation is bundled with each 
  distribution as an application that you can install locally. Links to the 
  documentation for the current stable release (1.0.2) are also provided on the 
  menu bar. Whenever possible, please help conserve our bandwidth, and install 
  the documentation locally.
  </blockquote>

  <p>
  The <a href="kickstart.html"><b>Kickstart FAQ</b></a> quickly answers 
  the most common questions about Struts. More technical questions are 
  covered by the <a href="newbie.html">Struts Newbie FAQ</a>, and online in the Struts 
  <a href="http://jguru.com/faq/Struts">JGuru FAQ</a> and 
  <a href="http://jguru.com/forums/Struts">Forum</a>.
  </p>

  <p>
  A concise <a href="userGuide/index.html"><b>Users Guide</b></a> is also provided 
  with the distribution. The User Guide introduces the Model-View-Controller 
  architecture, and how it relates to the major components of Struts. Several <b>Developer 
  Guides</b> are provided with the User Guide, to help you get started with the Struts JSP 
  tag extensions and utility packages. The User Guide also includes detailed installation 
  instructions and release notes for each version of the framework.
  </p>

  <p>
  For more detail about a specific class or package, the Struts 
  <a href="api/index.html"><b>Javadocs</b></a>
  are <b>surprisingly comprehensive and carefully maintained</b>. It is <i>strongly</i> recommended that 
  you refer to the 
  <a href="api/index.html">
  Javadoc</a> for each class as you begin to use it, to be sure important features 
  and options are not overlooked. <i>What you don't know, can't help you.</i>
  </p>

  <p>
  Of course, the only true documentation is the code itself. If you have any questions 
  about how Struts actually works, do not hesitate to <i>use the source</i>. For the 
  complete, buildable source code to the entire Struts framework, see the "src" folder in 
  the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2/src/">
  <b>Struts 1.0.2 source distribution</b></a>.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Struts <a href="#Involved">Mailing Lists</a> are an treasure trove of useful, 
  interactive information. The list tends to carry a high volume, so always check the 
  published documentation and 
  the <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-user%40jakarta.apache.org/">
  <b>MAILING LIST ARCHIVE</b></a> before posting a new question. Like as not, it's 
  already been asked and answered.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Struts <a href="resources.html"><b>Resources</b></a> page provides links to 
  everything else published about  Struts, including books, articles, tutorials, seminars, 
  and sample applications. There are also links to public sites "Powered by Struts" and
  a directory of professional Struts consultants.
  </p>

  <p>
  The Struts <a href="news.html"><b>News &amp; Status</b></a> page highlights current 
  events affecting framework, including new releases, proposals for new features, 
  and additions to the Resources page.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Acquiring Struts" href="Acquiring">

  <p>
  The <i>production release</i> of <strong>Struts 1.0.2</strong> is available in
  a convenient binary distribution and also with complete source code. In
  addition, a library distribution is available, which contains the latest
  Struts binaries without the sample applications, providing a smaller,
  faster download.
  </p>

  <ul>
  <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2">
  <b>Struts 1.0.2 Binary Distribution</b></a></li>
  <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2/lib">
  <b>Struts 1.0.2 Library Distribution</b></a></li>
  <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2/src">
  <b>Struts 1.0.2 Source Code Distribution</b></a></li>
  </ul>
  
  <p>
  Check the 
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/doc-1.0.2/release-notes-1.0.2.html">
  </a> for a summary of the changes since the Struts 1.0.1 release.
  </p>

  <p>
  <b>In addition to a Struts distribution,</b> you will need to ensure that
  you have downloaded and installed all of the
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/doc-1.0.2/installation.html#Prerequisites">
  prerequisite</a> software applications. Then, follow the appropriate instructions to
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/doc-1.0.2/installation.html#Installing">
  install and use a Struts binary 
  distribution</a> in your web application or for
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/doc-1.0.2/installation.html#Building">
  building Struts from the source  distribution</a>.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Nightly Builds" href="Builds">

  <p>
  For developers who are helping to develop Struts, or who just want 
  "the latest bits", the latest development version is made available each 
  morning. Use at your own risk!
  </p>

  <ul>
  <li>Nightly builds - Download the source directly via
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">
      Anonymous CVS</a>.</li>
  <li>Nightly builds - Download the binary distributions from
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly">
      here</a>.</li>
  <li>Nightly builds - Download the source distributions from
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly/src">
      here</a>.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>
  Be sure to check the 
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/release-notes.html">
  Release Notes</a> for the nightly builds so you know what you are getting!
  </p>

  <p>
  Access to the CVS source repository for Struts is available through both
  <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-struts/">web
  browser</a> and
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">CVS client</a>
  interfaces.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Reporting Bugs and Feature Requests" href="Bugs">

  <p>
  Tracking of bug reports and enhancement requests for Struts is handled 
  through the 
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/bugs.html">
  Apache Bug Database</a>. Please select <strong>Struts</strong> from the product 
  list, along with the details of which component of Struts you feel this report 
  relates to, and details of your operating environment. You will automatically be
  notified by email as the status of your bug or enhancement report changes.
  </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Getting Involved" href="Involved">

  <p>
  There are a number of ways to get more involved in the Struts
  community, including contributing to the future development of Struts.
  Check out the following resources:
  </p>
  <ul>
  <li><strong>STRUTS-USER Mailing List</strong> - Subscribe to this list
      to communicate with other developers that are using
      Struts for their own applications, including questions about the
      installation of Struts, and the usage of particular Struts features.
      [<a href="mailto:struts-user-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">Subscribe</a>]
      [<a href="mailto:struts-user-unsubscribe@jakarta.apache.org">Unsubscribe</a>]
      </li>
  <li><strong>STRUTS-DEV Mailing List</strong> - Subscribe to this
      mailing list to communicate with other developers interested in expanding
      and improving the functionality supported by Struts itself.
      [<a href="mailto:struts-dev-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">Subscribe</a>]
      [<a href="mailto:struts-dev-unsubscribe@jakarta.apache.org">Unsubscribe</a>]
      </li>
  <li><strong>STRUTS-USER Digest</strong> - Subscribe to this list
      to receive a daily digest of the Struts USER list. 
      [<a href="mailto:struts-user-digest-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">Subscribe</a>]
      [<a href="mailto:struts-user-digest-unsubscribe@jakarta.apache.org">Unsubscribe</a>]
      </li>
  <li><strong>STRUTS-USER Newgroup</strong> - The User list is also mirrored online, 
      so that you can participate <b>without</b> subscribing to the regular mailing 
      list.<br/>
      [<a href="http://news.basebeans.com/forums.jsp">Struts Newsgroup</a>]<br/>
      Our thanks to BaseBeans Engineering for providing this much-needed service!
      </li>
  <li><strong>Bug Reports and Feature Requests</strong> Use the
      <a href="#Bugs">Bug Reporting System</a> to submit these reports.</li>
  <li><strong>Patches and Modules</strong> - You can contribute patches and
      new modules to Struts by posting them to the STRUTS-DEV mailing list.
      After discussion and acceptance, one of the existing Committers will
      add your contribution to the Struts source code base (with credit to
      you, of course).</li>
  <li><strong>Become A Committer</strong> - If you wish to contribute directly
      to the development of Struts, and have commit access to the CVS source
      repository, you can be nominated (or nominate yourself) for Committer
      status on this project.  The rules by which committers are voted on are
      listed at the
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/guidelines/index.html">Jakarta
      web site</a>.</li>
  </ul>

  </section>


  </body>
</document>
