<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./kickstart.xml">
<properties>
<author>Ted Husted</author> 
<title>The Struts User's Guide - Newbie FAQ</title>
</properties>
<body> 
<chapter href="faq" name="Newbie FAQ"> 
<section href="contents" name="Table of Contents">
<p><font color="red"><b>UNDER CONSTRUCTION</b></font> (contributions welcome)</p>
<p>Here are answers to 21 common questions people ask when using Struts on 
their first project. <b>For an in-depth, searchable FAQ, visit our friends at <a href="http://www.jguru.com/faq/home.jsp?topic=Struts">JGuru</a>.</b></p>
  <ul>
    <li>Why is ActionForm a base class rather than an interface?</li>
    <li>Do I have to have a separate ActionForm bean for every HTML form?</li>
    <li>Can I use other beans or hashmaps with ActionForms?</li>
    <li>How can I prepopulate a form?</li>
    <li>Can I use multiple HTML form elements with the same name?</li>
    <li><a href="#actionforms">Why are my checkboxes not being set from ON to OFF?</a></li>
    <li>How can I capture binary or formatted values, like dates or telephone numbers?</li>
    <li>Why do my option lists disappear when validation fails?</li>
    <li><a href="#scriptlets">Can't I just create some of my JavaBeans in the JSP using a scriptlet?</a></li>
    <li>When is the best time to validate input?</li>
    <li>How can I avoid validating a form before data is entered?</li>
    <li>How can I create a "wizard" workflow?</li>
    <li>How can I "chain" Actions?</li>
    <li>Can I have an Action without a form?</li>
    <li>How do I access my database?</li>
    <li>How can I authenticate my users?</li>
    <li>Can I have multiple submit buttons on the same form?</li>
    <li>Why can't my Javascript submit a form?</li>
    <li>Can I create dynamic ActionFowards?</li>
    <li>How can I use my own (ActionForm, ActionForward, ActionMapping, ActionServlet) class?</li>
    <li>Do I have to use JSPs with my application?</li>
  </ul>
</section>

<section href="actionforms" name="Wither ActionForms?">
<p>
http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-user@jakarta.apache.org/msg19281.html<br/>
http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-user@jakarta.apache.org/msg19338.html<br/>
http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-user@jakarta.apache.org/msg20833.html<br/>
</p>
</section>

<section href="checkbox" name="Why are my checkboxes not being set from ON to OFF?">
<p>
A problem with a checkbox is that the browser will only include it in the request 
when it is checked. If it is not checked, the HTML specification suggests that it 
not be sent (i.e. omitted from the request). If the value of the checkbox is being 
persisted, either in a session bean or in the model, a checked box can never 
unchecked by a HTML form -- because the form can never send a signal to uncheck 
the box. The application must somehow ascertain that since the element was not 
sent that the corresponding value is unchecked.
</p>
<p>
The recommended approach for Struts applications is to use the reset method in the 
ActionForm to set all properties represented by checkboxes to null or false. The 
checked boxes submitted by the form will then set those properties to true. The 
omitted properties will remain false. Another solution is to use radio buttons 
instead, which always submit a value. 
</p>
<p>
It is important to note that the HTML specification recommends this same 
behavior whenever a control is not "successful". Any blank element in a HTML 
form is not guaranteed to submitted. It is therefor very important to set the 
default values for an ActionForm correctly, and to implement the reset method 
when the ActionForm might kept in session scope.
</p>
</section>

<section href="scriptlets" name="Can't I just create some of my JavaBeans in the JSP using a scriptlet?">
<p>
Struts is designed to encourage a 
<a href="http://www.javaworld.com/javaworld/jw-12-1999/f_jw-12-ssj-jspmvc.html">
Model 2/MVC architecture</a>. But there is nothing that prevents you from using Model 1 
techniques in your JavaServer Pages, so the answer  to the question is "Yes, you can". 
</p>
<p>
Though, using Model 1 techniques in a Struts application does go against the grain. 
The approach recommended by most Struts developers is to create and populate whatever 
objects the view may need in the Action, and then forward these through the request. 
Some objects may also be created and stored in the session or application context, 
depending on how they are used. 
</p>
<p>
Likewise, there is nothing to prevent you from using scriptlets along with JSP 
tags in your pages. Though, many Struts developers report writing very complex 
scriplet-free applications and recommend the JSP tag approach to others.
</p>
<p>
For help with Model 1 techniques and scriptlets, you might consider joining the 
<a href="http://archives.java.sun.com/jsp-interest.html">Javasoft JSP-interest 
mailing list</a>, where there are more people still using these approaches. 
</p>
</section>


</chapter></body></document>
