<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig McClanahan</author>
    <author email="mcooper@apache.org">Martin Cooper</author>
    <author email="husted@apache.org">Ted Husted</author>

    <title>New and Status</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="News &amp; Status">

<h3>01 Mar 2002  - Simper 0.2</h3>

<p>
Simper is a simple JDBC persistence mechanism for Java web apps. It
features many of the interesting features of EJB, such as automatic
transaction demarcation (by way of Servlet Filters), and automatic
change detection of database rows (by way of DynaBeans). Lastly, the
notation by which you reference rows, as well as relations between
tables, is extremely JSP friendly.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.netmeme.org/simper/">http://www.netmeme.org/simper/</a>
</p>
<p>
0.2 is not a new release (it's been out for about a month), but, a
SourceForge project has been set up, with mailing lists, CVS, etc., so
that others can discuss and contribute (as I am getting quite busy
lately)
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>



<h3><a name="20020212"></a>12 February 2002 - Stxx for transforming XML</h3>

<p>
<a href="http://www.oroad.com/opencode/">
<b>Struts for transforming XML with XSL</b></a> (stxx) is an extension of 
the Struts framework to enhance support for XML and XSL.
</p>
<p>
stxx sits on top of Struts, extending it's existing functionality to allow
Action classes to return XML that will be transformed by an XSL file.
</p>
<p>
The idea of stxx is to remove the need to be use JSP and TagLibs for the
presentation layer of this framework. However, stxx does not force you to go the
XML/XSL route, both technologies should work side by side.
</p>
<p>
So, adding XSL support to struts is ALMOST as simple as adding the following
tags to your struts-config.xml file:
</p>
<pre>
&lt;action path="/welcome"
        type="com.oroad.stxx.example.ExampleWelcomeAction"
        scope="request">
        &lt;forward name="success">
&lt;!-- 
    the transform tags take the XML returned by the Action
    and transform them. The transform tag used is determined
    by matching the user agent against the name attribute (or
    default if nothing matches)
-->
                &lt;transform name="default" path="/login.xsl"/>
                &lt;transform name="Mozilla" path="/login_netscape.xsl"/>
                &lt;transform name="MSIE" path="/login_msie.xsl"/>
        &lt;/forward>
&lt;/action>
</pre>
<p>
stxx features:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Enhances the &lt;forward> tag in the struts-config.xml file to allow
one to many &lt;transform> tags. These &lt;transform> tags represent 
the XSL file to be used depending on the user-agent of the 
browser accessing struts
</li><li>
A new class variable for the Action class, A JDOM Document, which 
you use to append your data in your Action class too. This 
Document object will be transformed by the XSL file in your 
&lt;transform> tag.
</li><li>
stxx automatically flattens the ApplicationResources file to XML 
and attaches it to the Document object returned by the new Action   
class.
</li><li>
stxx also automatically appends the request parameters and 
attributes, as well as ActionErrors as XML to the Document 
object.
</li>
</ul>
<p> 
Please note: stxx is a work in progress, however, at this point I've been using
it for about 4 months and it works great for me, I realize it might not fit
everyone elses needs. Please send me feedback, opinions, complains, etc.
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3><a name="20020211"></a>11 February 2002 - Struts 1.0.2 Released</h3>
<p>
The Struts team announces the release of Struts 1.0.2. This release is a
bug fix only release, which fixes a compatibility problem inadvertently introduced
with the previous 1.0.1 release. 
</p>
<p>
The binary distribution for this release is available 
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2/">
<b>here</b></a>
and the source distribution
is available 
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2/src/">
<b>here</b></a>. 
In addition, a library distribution, which consists of a minimal
binary distribution, without sample web applications or additional code, is
available 
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2/src/">
<b>here</b></a>. 
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>6 February 2002 - Struts Console v1.4</h3>
<p>
Struts Console version 1.4 is now available.
</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/">
http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/</a><br/>
<a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/struts-console-1.4.zip">
http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/struts-console-1.4.zip</a>
</p>
<p>
This release adds plugin support for the new Oracle
JDeveloper 9i IDE.  This release also adds significant
new funcionality to the "JSP Converter" and renames it
to "Page Converter".
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>26 January 2002 - Free Struts Development Tool</h3>
<p>
"ObjectAssembler Standard is focused on supporting developers whose sole
area of concern is developing Servlets, JSPs, JavaBeans and Struts
components. It provides a visual development and code synchronization
environment for the creation and assembly of these components into web
applications."
</p>
<p>
Here is the download page:<br/>
<a href="http://www.objectventure.com/products/objectassembler.html">
http://www.objectventure.com/products/objectassembler.html</a>
</p>
<p>
Here is a Viewlet showing some of ObjectAssembler's features:<br/>
<a href="http://www.objectventure.com/demo/IntroStruts_viewlet.html">
http://www.objectventure.com/demo/IntroStruts_viewlet.html</a>
</p>
<p>
Please give it a try and tell us what you think. We are currently working on
our next major release that will provide J2EE 1.3 support. We also plan to
support Struts as it evolves (multi-app support, etc.), so any input we
receive would make that support even better.
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3><a name="20020118"></a>18 Jan 2002 - Nested Taglib added to nightly build</h3>
<p>
Struts tags support a dotted notation to refer to a nested beans. The Nested 
Talib extends this notation to automatically include a parent tag. Instead of 
referring to a property as parent<strong>.</strong>child, "parent" can be 
defined with the <code>nest</code> tag, and other Struts tags within that 
tag can simply refer to the "child" property. Tags can be nested arbitarily 
deep. 
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>17 January 2002 - Chiki v0.23</h3>
<p>
Chiki is a Wiki-like webapp built using Struts. This is the first
publicly available release, so as much feedback as possible would be
greatly appreciated. 
</p>
<p> 
Chiki can be found at:<br/>
<a href="http://chiki.emaho.org">
http://chiki.emaho.org </a>
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>14 January 2002 - New Committer, Arron Bates </h3>
<p>
Arron Bates, known for his interesting and popular nesting extension to 
the Struts taglibs has been elected as a Struts Committer. 
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>13 Janaury 2002 - Scioworks Camino v1.0</h3>
<p>
We are pleased to announce the general availability of the Scioworks Camino 
v1.0, visual tool for Struts application development.
</p>
<p>
Download is available at <br/>
<a href="http://www.scioworks.com/scioworks_camino_download.html.">
http://www.scioworks.com/scioworks_camino_download.html.</a>
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3><a name="20020112.2"></a>12 Jan 2002 - MultiApp Capability Added</h3>
<p>
Support for multiple application modules has been added to the nightly build. 
Developers can now provide multiple Struts configuration files, each of which 
can defines its own "module prefix". All of the "context-relative" values in 
the Struts configuration are now "module-relative". Struts components which '
handle context-relative URIs now transparently handle module-relative URIs. 
</p>
<p>
Existing configuration files, JavaServer Pages, or Actions do not need to be 
changed to use this capability. The only change is to specify the module 
prefix to be used with each additional configuration. 
</p>
<p>
This feature allows different teams to work on different parts of an 
application at the same time, without conflict over the configuration file. 
It also allows Struts applications that were developed independantly to be 
easily merged. 
</p>
<p>
Formal documentation is pending. See the Mailing List Archive for details. 
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-dev@jakarta.apache.org/msg04354.html">
The BIG Check-In for Multi-App Support</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-dev@jakarta.apache.org/msg04773.html">
Action mappings and The BIG Check-In</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-dev@jakarta.apache.org/msg04740.html">
[proposal] Multi-app sources modifications</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/struts-dev@jakarta.apache.org/msg04460.html">
Struts Next</a></li>
</ul>
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3><a name="20020112"></a>12 Jan 2002 - Struts 1.0.1 Released</h3>
<p>
  The Struts team is proud to announce the release of Struts 1.0.1. This
  release is primarily a bug fix release, which fixes a number of known
  problems with the previous 1.0 release.
</p>
<p>
  The binary distribution for this release is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1/">here</a>
  and the source distribution is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1/src/">here</a>.
  In addition, a library distribution, which consists of a minimal binary distribution,
  without sample web applications or additional code, is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1/lib/">here</a>.
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3><a name="20020103"></a>03 Jan 2002 - Struts + Velocity + Tools</h3>
<p>
The first code for the new 
<a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-velocity-tools/">
Velocity Tool Subproject</a> is in and
can be found in CVS as jakarta-velocity-tools. The first 
functionality includes integration with Jakarta Struts as well as a
generic template-rendering servlet with tool support.
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>

<p align="center">
<a href="news_2001.html">
<b>MORE NEWS</b></a>
</p>

  </section>


</body>
</document>
