<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig McClanahan</author>
    <author email="mcooper@apache.org">Martin Cooper</author>
    <author email="husted@apache.org">Ted Husted</author>

    <title>New and Status</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="News &amp; Status">

<h3>18 January 2002 - Nested Taglib added to nightly build</h3>
<p>
Struts tags support a dotted notation to refer to a nested beans. The Nested 
Talib extends this notation to automatically include a parent tag. Instead of 
referring to a property as parent<strong>.</strong>child, "parent" can be 
defined with the <code>nest</code> tag, and other Struts tags within that 
tag can simply refer to the "child" property. Tags can be nested arbitarily 
deep. 
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>

<h3>14 January 2002 - New Committer, Arron Bates </h3>
<p>
Arron Bates, known for his interesting and popular nesting extension to 
the Struts taglibs has been elected as a Struts Committer. 
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>12 January 2002 - MultiApp Capability Added</h3>
<p>
Support for multiple application modules has been added to the nightly build. 
Developers can now provide multiple Struts configuration files, each of which 
can defines its own "module prefix". All of the "context-relative" values in 
the Struts configuration are now "module-relative". Struts components which '
handle context-relative URIs now transparently handle module-relative URIs. 
</p>
<p>
Existing configuration files, JavaServer Pages, or Actions do not need to be 
changed to use this capability. The only change is to specify the module 
prefix to be used with each additional configuration. 
</p>
<p>
This feature allows different teams to work on different parts of an 
application at the same time, without conflict over the configuration file. 
It also allows Struts applications that were developed independantly to be 
easily merged. 
</p>
<p>

 instead -- in other words, the request URI
  equals "context path" + "application prefix" + "local value".  This
  works even for the default sub-application, because its prefix is
  a zero-length string.

This works in the same fashion  which is similar to the  at the beginning of the
  context-relative URI (similar to the way that a servlet container
  chooses the web app to run based on the context path prefix of the
  request URI.

</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>

<h3>15 January 2002 - Nested Taglib added to nightly build</h3>
<p>

</p>
<p>
  
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>12 January 2002 - Struts 1.0.1 Released</h3>
<p>
  The Struts team is proud to announce the release of Struts 1.0.1. This
  release is primarily a bug fix release, which fixes a number of known
  problems with the previous 1.0 release.
</p>
<p>
  The binary distribution for this release is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1/">here</a>
  and the source distribution is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1/src/">here</a>.
  In addition, a library distribution, which consists of a minimal binary distribution,
  without sample web applications or additional code, is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1/lib/">here</a>.
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<h3>27 November 2001 - Struts 1.0.1-rc1 Released</h3>
<p>
  The first <strong>Release Candidate</strong> for Struts 1.0.1 is now
  available. This release fixes a number of known problems with the
  Struts 1.0 release.
</p>
<p>
  The binary distribution for this release candidate is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1-rc1/">here</a>
  and the source distribution is available
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.1-rc1/src/">here</a>.
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>

<h3>15 June 2001 - Struts 1.0 Released</h3>

<p>
As promised at JavaOne, the
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Struts</a> project team is proud
to announce the availability of <strong>Version 1.0</strong> of the
Struts Framework.  The binary distribution for Struts 1.0 is available
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0/">here</a>
and the source distribution is available
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0/src/">here</a>. 
A press release is also available.
</p>

<hr noshade="" size="1"/>

<h3>02 June 2001 - Struts 1.0-beta-3 Released </h3>

<p><strong>Struts 1.0-beta-3</strong> is a release candidate version of the
Struts Framework, likely to be the final beta prior to the Struts 1.0 Final
Release, which is currently scheduled for <strong>June 15, 2001</strong>.
Please help identify any remaining bugs that need to be fixed prior to
final release, and report them to our bug tracking system at
<a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/">http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/</a>.</p>

<p>The binary distribution of Struts 1.0-beta-3 is available
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0-b3/">here</a>,
and the source distribution of Struts 1.0-beta-3 is available
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0-b3/src/">here</a>.</p>

<hr noshade="" size="1"/>

<h3>19 May 2001 - Jakarta Struts 1.0-b2 Released</h3>

<p><strong>Struts 1.0-b2</strong> is an update release in preparation for a
final release of Struts 1.0 prior to JavaOne 2001.  The changes included are
documented in the
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/release-notes-1.0-b2.html">Release
Notes</a>.  Get your copy of this latest release
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0-b2/">here</a>.
</p>

<hr noshade="" size="1"/>

<h3>23 February 2001 - Struts 1.0 Beta 1 Released </h3>

<p>
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">Version 1.0-beta-1 of the Struts 
  Framework is now available for download.</a>
</p>

<p>
  Struts is an open source project, under the sponsorship of the Apache
  Software Foundation, to produce framework useful in building web
  applications with Java Servlet and JavaServer Pages (JSP) technology.
  Struts encourages application architectures based on the
  Model-View-Controller (MVC) design paradigm.
</p>

<hr noshade="" size="1"/>

  </section>

</body>
</document>
