<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./volunteers.xml">

<properties>
    <title>Who We Are - The Apache Struts Web Application Framework</title>
    <author>Ted Husted</author>
</properties>

<body>
<chapter name="Who We Are" href="whoWeAre">

<section name="The Meritocracy" href="meritocracy">

    <p>
    All work Struts is contributed by volunteers whose only motivation is 
    to help make Struts work even better, both for themselves and for rest of 
    the community.
    </p>

    <p>
    All contributions are welcome, and may discussed and posted the 
    mailing lists.
    The final decision of what becomes part of the official distribution is 
    made by a group of <a href="#committers">Committers</a>. 
    For more about Meritocracy, see the 
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/roles.html">Management page</a> 
    the Apache Jakarta Website.
    </p>

</section>

<section name="Source Code Contributors" href="contributors.source">

    <ul>
        <li>
            Craig R. McClanahan
        </li>
        
        <li>
            David Geary
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Mike Schachter
        </li>
        <li>
            Ted Husted
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Rob Leland
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Martin Cooper
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Arron Bates
        </li>
        
        <li>        
            Cedric Dumoulin
        </li>
        
        <li>
            David Winterfeldt
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Arun M. Thomas
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Chris Audley
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Dominique Plante
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Don Clasen
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Florent Carpentier
        </li>
        
        <li>
            James Holmes
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Jeff Hutchison
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Jimmy Larsson
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Luis Arias
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Marius Barduta
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Niall Pemberton
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Ralph Schaer
        </li>
        
        <li>
            Sean M. Kelley
        </li>
        
        <li>
            David Graham
        </li>
        
        <li>
            James Turner
        </li>

    </ul>

</section>

<section name="Documentation Contributors" href="contributors.documentation">
<ul>

        <li>
            Craig R. McClanahan
        </li>

        <li>
            David Geary
        </li>

        <li>
            Mike Schachter
        </li>

        <li>
            Ted Husted
        </li>

        <li>
            Martin Cooper
        </li>

        <li>
            Arron Bates
        </li>

        <li>
            Cedric Dumoulin
        </li>

        <li>
            David Winterfeldt
        </li>

        <li>
            Chris Assenza
        </li>

        <li>
            dIon Gillard
        </li>

        <li>
            Dominique Plante
        </li>

        <li>
            Ed Burns
        </li>

        <li>
            Eric Wu
        </li>

        <li>
            James DeVries
        </li>

        <li>
            John Rousseau
        </li>

        <li>
            John Ueltzhoeffer
        </li>

        <li>
            Larry McCay
        </li>

        <li>
            Mark Budai
        </li>

        <li>
            Matthias Kerkhoff
        </li>

        <li>
            Paul Runyan
        </li>

        <li>
            Robert Hayden
        </li>

        <li>
            Robert Leland
        </li>

        <li>
            Stanley Santiago
        </li>

        <li>
            Wong Kok Kai
        </li>

        <li>
            Donald Ball
        </li>

        <li>
            Dan Walker
        </li>

        <li>
            Eddie Bush
        </li>

        <li>
            Yann Cebron
        </li>

        <li>
            David Graham
        </li>

        <li>
            Steve Ditlinger
        </li>
        
        <li>
            David M. Karr
        </li>

        <li>
            Tim O'Brien
        </li>

        <li>
            Edgar Dollin
        </li>
    
    </ul>
</section>

<section name="Active Committers" href="committers">

    <ul>
    
        <li>
            <b>Craig R. McClanahan</b> (craigmcc at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Ted Husted</b> (husted at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Rob Leland</b> (rleland at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Vincent Massol</b> (vmassol at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Cedric Dumoulin</b> (cedric.dumoulin at lifl.fr)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Martin Cooper</b> (martinc at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>David Winterfeldt</b> (dwinterfeldt at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Oleg Alexeev</b> (oalexeev at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Arron Bates</b> (arron at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>James Holmes</b> (jholmes at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>David M. Karr</b> (dmkarr at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>Eddie Bush</b> (ekbush at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>David Graham</b> (dgraham at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>James Mitchell</b> (jmitchell at apache.org)
        </li>

        <li>
            <b>James Turner</b> (turner at blackbear.com)
        </li>

    </ul>
    
</section>

<section name="Emeritus Committers" href="comitters.emeritus">

<ul>

    <li>
        David Geary
    </li>
    
    <li>
        Luis Arias
    </li>
    
    <li>
        Pierre Delilse
    </li>
    
    <li>
        Michael Schachter
    </li>

</ul>

</section>

<section name="More About Us" href="about">

    <h3><a name="craigmcc">Craig R. McClanahan -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    I've been involved with servlet and JSP technology since around 1998.  
    It started out that I needed a way to build some web applications for 
    several projects, and liked Java a lot better than the alternatives.  
    I also liked theprice tag of open source software, and started using 
    Apache JServ -- later , getting involved in the project (like many 
    people, I was whining about the twelve months it took to get from version
    0.9 to version 1.0, and my son said "Dad, you know Java -- go help them 
    finish it!" -- so I did :-).
    </p>

    <p>For quite a while, I was participating a lot the JSP-INTEREST and   
    SERVLET-INTEREST <a href="http://archives.java.sun.com">mailing lists</a>, 
    especially the topic of good architectures for web applications.  
    I was disgusted with the hash that many beginners created when they used 
    (or abused) scriptlets in JSP pages, and built (for my former employer) a 
    pretty comprehensive framework that could considered ("Struts 0.01 
    without the custom tags").  
    It was proprietary code, but I was able to describe the concepts, and 
    there started to a feeling the lists that this "Model 2" thing was 
    pretty cool -- but there were no good examples to look at, so it was 
    mostly hand waving types of discussions.
    </p>

    <p>
    Over the same time period, I got involved as an individual contributor in 
    the <a href="http://java.sun.com/jcp">Java Community Process</a>, and 
    joined the expert group that defined the servlet 2.2 and JSP 1.1 specs.  
    Sun was impressed enough to offer me a job as the technical lead the 
    team within Sun (currently five other individuals) that works 
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Tomcat</a>  -- the architecture 
    for Catalina, which is the servlet container part of Tomcat 4.0, is also 
    mine -- so I am in the really nice position of getting paid to work 
    open source software :-).  
    And, participate the expert groups for Servlet 2.3 and JSP 1.2.  
    And, speak at various conferences, including ApacheCon and JavaOne.  
    And, talk to groups within Sun about using Struts and JSP/servlet 
    technology.
    And ... (there's some really interesting  things being considered for the 
    future).
    </p>

    <p>
    The original design of what came to Struts has been in my head for a 
    long time, since those interesting mailing list discussions, but the first 
    version of the actual code was written my laptop a Memorial Day 
    weekend vacation trip (end of May, 2000) to the Oregon coast -- in between 
    watching the surf and having the house shaken by a windstorm at night.  
    Since then, it has gathered attention and popularity as we approach our 
    first official release, and it delights me to see my "baby" grow up so 
    well :-).  
    Of course, it is no longer just me -- there have been incredible numbers 
    of good ideas from all over, and a peek at the TODO list for 1.1 says that 
    even more good stuff is coming in the future.
    </p>

    <p>One motivation factor was 
    <a href="http://www.servlets.com/soapbox/problems-jsp.html"> Jason 
    Hunter's</a> article about the Problems with JSP. 
    Jason and I get along fine, even though we have different preferences 
    about presentation technologies.  
    Besides being the author of a very popular book about servlets, with a 
    second edition coming soon, Jason is also the representative for the
    Apache Software Foundation the Executive Committee of the Java 
    Community Process.
    </p>

    <p>
    Personally, I live in Portland, Oregon (even though my team at Sun is 
    mostly in Cupertino, CA -- staying here was part of the job deal :-).  
    I like to support Oregon sports teams (Oregon State Beavers, Oregon Ducks, 
    Portland Trailblazers) and work cool software.
    </p>

    <p>
    I figured out I was getting pretty old when I realized that 2000 was the 
    25th year I had been paid to work in some aspect of software development 
    :-).  
    I've got a son who is a full-time software developer (primarily in PHP so
    far, but I'm going to corrupt him with Java eventually :-), and a daughter 
    in college.
    I'll happily let the other committers speak for themselves.
    </p>

    <h3><a name="mschachter">Mike Schachter -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    I'm currently a student of computer science at Drexel University in 
    Philadelphia, PA.
    I've been working at HP Middleware, formerly Bluestone Software for 3 
    years programming in Java and recently J2EE technologies.  
    I'm a full time worker from September until April and a student and part 
    time worker from April until August.
    In my spare time I've been known to run monkey-knife fights in a shady 
    south philly warehouse.  
    Err...
    I mean... nothing.
    </p>

    <h3><a name="husted">Ted Husted -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    My primary interest in Struts is to put it to work writing lots of
    real-life Web applications:-) 
    To do that effectively means having good documentation and code samples at 
    my fingertips, so that's been my focus with the Struts product so far.
    </p>

    <p>
    I've been writing software for hire since 1984, but only recently jumped
    the Java bandwagon. 
    My initial interest was with electronic publishing, and started by 
    converting my various print projects to electronic media. 
    The "Information Superhighway" was still the private stomping ground of 
    Universities and government agencies then. 
    The rest of us had to make do with diskettes and bulletin boards.
    </p>

    <p>
    Between 1985 and 1994, I created and marketed several software products
    for publishing disk, the most popular being "Dart" and "Iris". 
    In 1992, Dart was awarded the Digital Quill for software excellence,
    featured in PC Magazine (February 1992), and bundled with McGraw Hill's 
    bookset,"Paperless Publishing" by Colin Hayes (McGraw Hill 1994). 
    Dart won a second Digital Quill in 1993. 
    Several titles that used Iris for a publishing system have also won awards 
    and been widely distributed, including "Hermitville USA." 
    I was also fortunate to find kindred souls CompuServe and America 
    Online, who helped me pioneer resources areas there in 1993 and 1994 for 
    the nascent electronic publishing industry.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    I finally cut loose the Internet in 1995, launching Epub News, an
    electronic newspage about electronic publishing. After taking several
    private contracts, I opened the Husted dot Com Website (www.husted.com)
    in 1996. 
    I've drifted away from electronic books, but have noticed that several 
    products are now making their way into the consumer mainstream -- as 
    usual, I was twenty minutes into the future:-)
    </p>
    
    <p>
    My favorite all-time project is the Hitchhikers Guide to Science Fiction. 
    This was one of my earliest hypertext projects (it started as a print-book 
    idea), and I had a lot of fun bringing it forward onto the Web. 
    (Now, if I only had time to bring it current and dress it up!)
    </p>

    <p>
    My favorite all-time client is WXXI Public Broadcasting Council, where 
    I've served as the station's Webmaster. 
    WXXI provides public broadcasting services for television and radio, and
    we are working to do the same online. 
    Along with providing companion Web sites for every WXXI production, we 
    stream both our AM and FM signals, in both Real and QuickTime, with online 
    archives in the works. 
    It's a long journey, but we've taken the first steps. 
    I'm responsible for most of the regular updates to the site, and much of 
    the overall layout and design. 
    We're grateful to have won the PBS award for best Web site in our market 
    for two years running.
    </p>

    <p>
    Our most ambitious projects at WXXI have been Spring Marketplace 2000 and 
    the NY Election Finder. 
    For Spring Marketplace, we put our annual auction fully online for 
    simultaneous telephone and Website bidding. 
    NY Election, we offered not only the usual election-finder application,
    but collected voter registration records from around the state, so
    people could also check their registration status and polling place. 
    I developed the Web-enabled database applications for both projects.
    </p>

    <p>
    Currently, I'm expanding the WXXI online auction software into a complete 
    package for hosting online auctions as fund-raisers; this is to an 
    open-source project called Gavel, and, of course, is based Struts. 
    </p>

    <h3><a name="cedric">Cedric Dumoulin -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    As a dreamer / researcher I have thought a lot about a framework like 
    Struts.
    But, as a lazy developer I have first checked what already exists, and I 
    have found Struts. 
    Struts goals fulfilled nearly all I needed for my (now old) portal 
    project, except the capability to reuse and assemble easily pieces of
    pages or components. 
    So, I have proposed the Components framework. 
    This framework can seen as a superset of the Templates tag library 
    contributed by David Geary, and contains lot of interesting features.
    </p>

    <p>
    From a professional point of view, I have a Ph.D. in computer science. 
    I have worked for 3 years in the R&amp;D department of a worldwide company 
    developing Internet banking solutions. 
    I am now a researcher at a university, and work European research 
    projects. 
    My main research interest is WWW, Distributed Systems and Object Oriented 
    Design. 
    When developing code, I always try to first propose reusable pieces of 
    code.
    </p>

    <h3><a name="martinc">Martin Cooper -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    Currently, I'm a Principal Software Engineer at Tumbleweed Communications,
    working the Messaging Management System. 
    Early last year (2000), I was working the architecture for a new web-
    based administration system for the product, and headed in the direction 
    of servlets and JSP. 
    I joined the JSP-INTEREST and SERVLET-INTEREST mailing lists to see what 
    was going in those respective areas.
    </p>

    <p>
    Before too long, some interesting discussions started up around the topic
    of Model 2 architectures. 
    Model 2 sounded like the right way to go about things, and I followed 
    those discussions closely. 
    I was, however, still looking for a "leg up" - something to give me that 
    core which to build.
    </p>

    <p>
    Then, in May, I saw a post to JSP-INTEREST from Craig McClanahan entitled
    something like "New Jakarta-Struts Subproject", and describing Struts, and
    his vision for it. 
    I hopped right over to the Jakarta web site and signed up for the mailing 
    list. 
    Before long, I realized this was exactly what I had been looking for.
    </p>

    <p>
    Now, a year or so later, we have a team of people, which I am the 
    technical lead, just finishing up our web-based administration system as 
    Struts reaches its 1.0 release. 
    And I am still firmly convinced that I made the right decision in going 
    with Struts in the first place.
    </p>

    <p>
    Like anyone else, my first postings to the struts-user list were questions
    to help me understand how to do things, and why Struts is the way it is.
    Over time, reading the lists and also the source code, and working my 
    own fairly large web application, I came to the point where I could answer
    questions too. 
    Now, I'm glad to able to give something back to the Struts community by 
    helping others understand, and also by contributing ideas and code to help
    make Struts even better than it already is.
    </p>

    <h3><a name="dwinterfeldt">David Winterfeldt -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    As I worked web based projects I started looking for something
    that would really help save time during development.  
    I ran across Struts in the Summer of 2000 and decided it was a good 
    solution for web development.  
    As I used Struts it really helped to remove a lot of the repetitive work,
    but validation still seemed very repetitive.
    I had an idea to create validation rules in an xml file and have them
    easily integrated with Struts.  
    It started out simple and continued to develop over time.  
    The validation project was eventually incorporated into Struts and the 
    core was moved to Jakarta Commons. 
    I'm happy to see Struts continue to grow and develop.
    </p>

    <p>
    I currently am employed at Forbes.com.  
    I occasionally get to do some internal projects using Struts.  
    The last interesting project was a publishing system using Message Driven 
    EJBs in JBoss and Struts was used to display the status of each publishing 
    process.
    </p>

    <h3><a name="rleland">Rob Leland -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    I have gone from Unix -to- Windows -to- Unix based development about ever 
    6 years now. 
    When moving to Windows I was amazed at how primitive the OS was compared 
    to Unix. 
    While developing for Win32 I had the pleasure of discovering Delphi and 
    developed many GUI/databases, and a few telephony, Internet enabled
    applications. 
    I remain impressed with its design. 
    I am always able to develop a simple  elegant solution with the language, 
    much like the language itself. 
    I was convinced after 10 years of development with C/C++ that it was a 
    kinder gentler language. 
    When I recently returned to Unix the platform hadn't changed one bit.
    </p>

    <p>
    Then in July 2000 I decided to move into Java, and the Web development.
    This is after using the web since 1992/1985 and occasionally teaching 
    classes it since 1994.
    I came as a consultant to take over a JSP based application. I realized
    it had been written with the equivalent of "goto's"(Model 1) and had to 
    redesigned. 
    I searched for a better way to design the code and by late August I had 
    found Struts.
    </p>

    <p>
    To date I have mainly served to pitch in odds and ends.  
    I continue to amazed at the committers' generous contributions of time, 
    insight, and good will. 
    I am fortunate to part of the struts team. 
    </p>

    <h3><a name="dgraham">David Graham -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    I, like many others, discovered Struts when contemplating writing my own
    MVC Java framework for the web.  
    Struts had everything I needed and more so I scrapped plans for my own and 
    joined the mailing lists.  
    After playing with it for several months I started submitting 
    documentation and a few source patches.
    I'm excited about helping Struts evolve and am continually amazed by the 
    framework and the community surrounding it.
    </p>

    <h3><a name="jturner">James Turner -- Committer</a></h3>

    <p>
    I discovered Struts somewhat by accident.  In 2001 I began writing a
    book for SAMS on JSP web development (MySQL and JSP Web Development),
    and as part of it, I decided to write a chapter on Struts in the
    advanced section.  In the process of learning enough about Struts to
    write about it, I realized that it could simplify some of the projects
    that I was working on for clients.</p>
    <p>
    After a half a year of working with Struts, I was asked by SAMS to write
    another book, this time concentrating on Struts specifically.  That book,
    co-authored with a former co-worker named Kevin Bedell, became Struts
    Kick Start.</p>
    <p>
    In the process of writing that book, I began to realize that there were
    things I could do to contribute to Struts beyond writing about it.  One
    thing in particular was to clean up and add some functionality to the
    Commons Validator project, which eventually led to me release-managing
    (with a lot of help!) the Commons Validator 1.0 release.</p>
    <p>
    More generally, I've been a software developer for over 22 years, starting
    with work as a Research Specialist at the MIT AI Lab.  I spent nearly a
    decade working in LISP, before moving on to C/Unix, a stint managing the
    Web Site for the Christian Science Monitor, and finally Java based
    e-Commerce development, which has kept me busy for the last five years.</p>
    <p>
    In addition to the two books mentioned above, I also write for a number of
    publications, including WIRED and the aforementioned Christian Science 
    Monitor.  You can get a look at my portfolio 
    <a href="http://www.blackbear.com/monitor.html">here</a></p>

</section>

<section>
    <p align="right">
    Next: <a href="status.html">Development Roadmap</a>
    </p>
</section>

</chapter></body></document>
