<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./release-plan-1.1-b3.xml">

  <properties>
    <author>Martin F N Cooper</author>
    <title>Struts Release Plan (Version 1.1-b3)</title>
  </properties>

  <body>


  <section name="Objective" href="Objective">

  <p><font size="-2">$Id: release-plan-1.1b3.xml,v 1.2 2002/12/17 05:46:14 martinc Exp $</font></p>

  <p>The objective of the <strong>Struts 1.1 Beta 3</strong> release is to
  create a milestone release against which a final series of bug fixes and
  documentation updates can occur before a <strong>Struts 1.1 Final</strong>
  release is created.</p>

  </section>


  <section name="The Plan" href="Plan">

  <p>A number of new features have been added to the nightly builds since the
  second Beta release of Struts 1.1, and many bugs have been fixed. It is time,
  therefore, to take the next step in the release process, and make the latest
  code base available as a third Beta release. The goal is to move towards a
  release candidate and then a final <strong>Struts 1.1</strong> release as
  soon as is practicable.</p>

  <p>Therefore, the following release plan is proposed for Struts 1.1 Beta 3:
  </p>
  <ul>
  <li><em>Code Freeze / Tag Date</em> - Saturday, December 21, 2002</li>
  <li><em>Release Manager</em> - Martin Cooper</li>
  <li><em>Release Announcement</em> - To the following mailing lists:
      <ul>
      <li>announcements@jakarta.apache.org</li>
      <li>struts-dev@jakarta.apache.org</li>
      <li>struts-user@jakarta.apache.org</li>
      </ul></li>
  </ul>

  </section>


  <section name="Release Criteria" href="Criteria">

  <p>Prior to the release of Struts 1.1 Beta 3, the following action items
  must be completed:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>The Struts 1.1 Release Notes document shall be updated to describe
      substantial changes and improvements since the Struts 1.0.2 release,
      along with associated updates to the main Struts Documentation
      Application pages describing the new release.</li>
  <li>All of the Struts example applications that are included with the release
      shall operate successfully in the following servlet containers:
      <ul>
      <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Tomcat 3.3.1</a></li>
      <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Tomcat 4.0.6</a></li>
      <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat">Tomcat 4.1.12</a></li>
      </ul></li>
  <li>A release vote shall take place on the STRUTS-DEV mailing list to
      approve this plan.  The release vote MUST pass by "Majority Approval"
      of Struts committers.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>Prior to the release of a subsequent Struts 1.1 release candidate, the
  following action items must be completed:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>All <a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/">Bugzilla</a> bug reports
      against Struts 1.1 nightly builds MUST be marked as "Resolved", with any
      of the legal Bugzilla resolutions (FIXED, INVALID, WONTFIX, LATER,
      REMIND, WORKSFORME).</li>
  <li>Bug reports that are resolved as LATER or REMIND will include comments
      as to whether those specific issues will be dealt with in a subsequent
      beta, release candidate, or final release, or whether they will be
      scheduled for consideration in a subsequent release time frame.</li>
  </ul>

  </section>


  <section name="Bugs To Be Addressed" href="Bugs">

  <p>The following bugs must be addressed before Final Release of Struts 1.1.</p>

  <table>

    <!-- Custom tags -->
    <tr>
      <td colspan="2"><strong>Custom Tags</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">11021</td>
	  <td>ActionForward or &lt;html:link&gt; tag does not support absolute URIs</td>
	</tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">12302</td>
	  <td>Sporadic error in html:form action attribute</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">12470</td>
      <td>Web Site Cancel does not work correctly when using dynamic validation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">15044</td>
      <td>Taglib - Index Attribute in html:Checkbox doesn't set correctly</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">15196</td>
      <td>Bug on the RequestUtils.computeParameters using a DynaValidatorForm as map of the parameter</td>
    </tr>

    <!-- Controller -->
    <tr>
      <td colspan="2"><strong>Controller</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">12871</td>
	  <td>ExceptionHandler does not obey controller inputForward rule</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">14054</td>
	  <td>Rename "Application" components to "Module"</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">14669</td>
	  <td>reset() in DynaActionForm act the same as ActionForm</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">14749</td>
	  <td>Action "input" not starting with '/' and not a valid forward will cause an internal server error</td>
    </tr>

    <!-- Documentation -->
    <tr>
      <td colspan="2"><strong>Documentation</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">10537</td>
	  <td>[:TODO:] sections</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">15167</td>
	  <td>Updated Action documentation</td>
    </tr>

    <!-- File Upload -->
    <tr>
      <td colspan="2"><strong>File Upload</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">2017</td>
	  <td>Text entered in forms using multi-part/formdata cannot be utf8</td>
    </tr>

    <!-- Utilities -->
    <tr>
      <td colspan="2"><strong>Utilities</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">11932</td>
	  <td>(Message Resource is not multi-app aware) Multi-Resource not work in Multi-Appliction config environment</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">14800</td>
	  <td>Fix initialization bug and add size parameter to form-property</td>
    </tr>

    <!-- Unknown -->
    <tr>
      <td colspan="2"><strong>Unknown</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td width="75">14042</td>
	  <td>Unknown Memory leaks with JBoss 3.x +(Tomcat/Jetty)</td>
    </tr>

  </table>

  </section>


  </body>

</document>
