<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./index.xml">

  <properties>
    <author>Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <title>The Struts Framework Project</title>
  </properties>

  <body>


  <section name="Welcome to Struts" href="Welcome">

  <p>Welcome to the Struts Framework!  The goal of this project
  is to provide an open source framework useful in building web applications
  with Java <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet">Servlet</a> and
  <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp">JavaServer Pages</a> (JSP)
  technology.  Struts encourages appliation architectures based on the
  Model-View-Controller (MVC) design paradigm, colloquially known as
  <i>Model 2</i> in discussions on various servlet and JSP related
  mailing lists.</p>

  <p>Struts includes the following primary areas of functionality:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>A controller servlet that dispatches requests to appropriate
      <strong>Action</strong> classes provided by the application
      developer.</li>
  <li>JSP custom tag libraries, and associated support in the controller
      servlet, that assists developers in creating interactive form-based
      applications.</li>
  <li>Utility classes to support XML parsing, automatic population of
      JavaBeans properties based on the Java reflection APIs, and
      internationalization of prompts and messages.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>Struts is part of the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">Jakarta
  Project</a>, sponsored by the
  <a href="http://www.apache.org">Apache Software Foundation</a>.  The
  official Struts home page is at
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts">http://jakarta.apache.org/struts</a>.
  </p>

  </section>


  <section name="Acquiring Struts" href="Acquiring">

  <p><strong>NEW!</strong> - A milestone release, <strong>Version 0.5</strong>
  of Struts has been created and made available at
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v0.5">
  http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v0.5</a>.  This
  release will provide a stable basis for current projects being developed
  on Struts, while (sometimes incompatible) changes are occurring on the
  main code branch leading up to a <strong>Version 1.0</strong> release later.
  You can track the progress towards <strong>Version 1.0</strong>, and get
  early warning about new features and changes, by monitoring the
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/release.html">Release Notes</a>
  that are posted on the Struts project web site, as well as included in the
  nightly build distributions.</p>

  <p>You can acquire binary and source distributions of Struts from the
  following locations:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>Download the source directly via
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">
      Anonymous CVS</a>.</li>
  <li>Download nightly binary distributions from
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly">
      here</a>.</li>
  <li>Download nightly source distributions from
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly/src">
      here</a>.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>Access to the CVS source repository for Struts is available through both
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/cvsweb/index.cgi/jakarta-struts/">web
  browser</a> and
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/getinvolved/cvsindex.html">CVS client</a>
  interfaces.</p>

  <p>In addition to the Struts distribution, you will need to ensure that
  you have downloaded and installed all of the
  <a href="installation.html#Prerequisites">prerequisite</a> software
  applications.  Then, follow the appropriate instructions to
  <a href="installation.html#Building">build Struts from the source
  distribution</a>, or <a href="installation.html#Installing">install and
  use a Struts binary distribution</a> in your web application.</p>

  </section>


  <section name="Reporting Bugs and Feature Requests" href="Bugs">

  <p>Thanks to the gracious efforts of
  <a href="mailto:nick@cortexity.com">Nick Bauman</a> and his employer,
  Cortexity, there is now an interim bug tracking system available for
  all of the Jakarta projects (including Struts).  To report a bug, or
  request a feature enhancement, simply point your browser at:
  <a href="http://znutar.cortexity.com">
  http://znutar.cortexity.com</a>.  When filling out a bug report
  or feature request, please follow these simple rules:</p>
  <ul>
  <li>From the list of projects and categories, select one of the following
      entries:
      <ul>
      <li>Struts / Feature Requests / New Features</li>
      <li>Struts / Feature Requests / Enhancement</li>
      <li>Struts / Bug Report / New Bug Report</li>
      </ul></li>
  <li>For the <code>Project Release</code> field, enter the Struts version
      number (such as <strong>0.5</strong>) if you are using a released
      version, or the date included in the filename of a nightly distribution
      (such as <strong>20000922</strong>) if you are using that.</li>
  </ul>

  </section>


  <section name="Getting Involved" href="Involved">

  <p>There are a number of ways to get more involved in the Struts
  community, including contributing to the future development of Struts.
  Check out the following resources:</p>
  <ul>
  <li><strong>STRUTS-USER Mailing List</strong> - Subscribe to the
      <a href="mailto:struts-user-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">STRUTS-USER</a>
      mailing list to communicate with other developers that are using
      Struts for their own applications, including questions about the
      installation of Struts, and the usage of particular Struts features.</li>
  <li><strong>STRUTS-DEV Mailing List</strong> - Subscribe to the
      <a href="mailto:struts-dev-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">STRUTS-DEV</a>
      mailing list to communicate with other developers interested in expanding
      and improving the functionality supported by Struts itself.</li>
  <li><strong>Bug Reports and Feature Requests</strong> Use the
      <a href="#Bugs">Bug Reporting System</a> to submit these reports.</li>
  <li><strong>Patches and Modules</strong> - You can contribute patches and
      new modules to Struts by posting them to the STRUTS-DEV mailing list.
      After discussion and acceptance, one of the existing Committers will
      add your contribution to the Struts source code base (with credit to
      you, of course).</li>
  <li><strong>Become A Committer</strong> - If you wish to contribute directly
      to the development of Struts, and have commit access to the CVS source
      repository, you can be nominated (or nominate yourself) for Committer
      status on this project.  The rules by which committers are voted on are
      listed at the
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/guidelines/index.html">Jakarta
      web site</a>.</li>
  </ul>

  </section>


  </body>
</document>
