<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./building_controller.xml">

  <properties>
    <author>Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author>Mike Schachter</author>
    <author>Ted Husted</author>
    <author>Martin Cooper</author>
    <author>Ed Burns</author>
    <title>The Struts User's Guide - Building Controller Components</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>  
  <chapter name="4. Building Controller Components" href="building_controller">
  
      <section name="4.1 Overview" href="overview">
        
        <p>
          Now that we understand how to construct the Model and View components
        of your application, it is time to focus on the <code>Controller</code>
        components.  Struts includes a servlet that implements the primary function
        of mapping a request URI to an <code>Action</code> class.  Therefore, your
        primary responsibilities related to the Controller are:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>Write an <code>Action</code> class for each logical request that may 
            be received (extend <code>org.apache.action.Action</code>).</li>
        <li>Configure a ActionMapping (in XML) for each logical request that may 
            be submitted. The XML configuration file is usually named
            <code>struts-config.xml</code>.</li>
        <li>Update the web application deployment descriptor file (in XML)
            for your application to include the necessary Struts components.</li>
        <li>Add the appropriate Struts components to your application.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    
    <section name="4.2 Action Classes" href="action_classes">
      
      <p>The <code>Action</code> class defines two methods that could be
        executed depending on your servlet environment:
      </p>

<pre>
public ActionForward perform(ActionMapping mapping,
                             ActionForm form,
                             ServletRequest request,
                             ServletResponse response)
  throws IOException, ServletException;

public ActionForward perform(ActionMapping mapping,
                             ActionForm form,
                             HttpServletRequest request,
                             HttpServletResponse response)
  throws IOException, ServletException;
</pre>
      
      <p>
        Most projects would only use the "HttpServletRequest" version. 
      </p>
      <p>
        The goal of an <code>Action</code> class is to process a request, via 
        its <code>perform()</code> method, and return an <code>ActionForward</code> object 
        that identifies where control should be forwarded (e.g. a JSP) to provide 
        the appropriate response. In the <i>MVC/Model 2</i> design pattern,
        a typical <code>Action</code> class will often implement logic like the following
        in its <code>perform()</code> method:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Validate the current state of the user's session (for example, checking
            that the user has successfully logged on).  If the <code>Action</code>
            class finds that no logon exists, the request can be forwarded to
            the JSP page that displays the username and password prompts for
            logging on.  This could occur because a user tried to enter an 
            application "in the middle" (say, from a bookmark), or because the
            session has timed out, and the servlet container created a new one.</li>
        <li>If validation is not complete,
            validate the form bean properties as needed.  If a problem is found,
            store the appropriate error message keys as a request attribute, and
            forward control back to the input form so that the errors can be
            corrected.</li>
        <li>Perform the processing required to deal with this request (such as
            saving a row into a database).  This can be done by logic code embedded within
            the <code>Action</code> class itself, but should generally be performed
            by calling an appropriate method of a business logic bean.</li>
        <li>Update the server-side objects that will be used to create the next
            page of the user interface (typically request scope or session scope
            beans, depending on how long you need to keep these items available).</li>
        <li>Return an appropriate <code>ActionForward</code> object that identifies
            the JSP page to be used to generate this response, based on the newly
            updated beans.  Typically, you will acquire a reference to such an
            object by calling <code>findForward()</code> on either the
            <code>ActionMapping</code> object you received (if you are using a
            logical name local to this mapping), or on the controller servlet
            itself (if you are using a logical name global to the application).</li>
      </ul>
        
      <p>
        Design issues to remember when coding <code>Action</code> classes
        include the following:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>The controller servlet creates only one instance of your
            <code>Action</code> class, and uses it for all requests.  Thus,
            you need to code your <code>Action</code> class so that it operates
            correctly in a multi-threaded environment, just as you must code a
            servlet's <code>service()</code> method safely.</li>
        <li>The most important principle that aids in thread-safe coding is to
            use only local variables, not instance variables, in your
            <code>Action</code> class.  Local variables are created on a
            stack that is assigned (by your JVM) to each request thread, so
            there is no need to worry about sharing them.</li>
        <li>The beans that represent the Model of your system may throw exceptions
            due to problems accessing databases or other resources.
            You should trap all such exceptions
            in the logic of your <code>perform()</code> method, and log them to the
            application logfile (along with the corresponding stack trace) by
            calling:<br />
            <code>servlet.log("Error message text", exception);</code></li>
        <li>As a general rule, allocating scarce resources and keeping them across
            requests from the same user (in the user's session) can cause
            scalability problems.  You should strive to release such resources
            (such as database connections) prior to forwarding control to the
            appropriate View component -- even if a bean method you have called
            throws an exception.</li>
      </ul>
        
      <p>
        In addition, you will want to guard against <code>Action</code> classes
        that are too large.  The easiest way for this to happen is to embed your
        functional logic in the <code>Action</code> class itself, rather than
        coding it in separate business logic beans.  Besides making the
        <code>Action</code> class itself hard to understand and maintain, this
        approach also makes it harder to re-use the business logic code, because
        it is embedded inside a component (the <code>Action</code> class) that
        is tied to being executed in a web application environment.
      </p>

      <p>
        An <code>Action</code> can be factored into several local methods, so long as all 
        properties needed are passed in the method signatures. The JVM 
        handles such properties using the stack, and so they are thread-safe. 
      </p>
        
      <p>
        The example application included with Struts stretches this design
        principle somewhat, because the business logic itself is embedded in the
        <code>Action</code> classes.  This should be considered something of a
        bug in the design of the sample application, rather than an intrinsic
        feature of the Struts architecture, or an approach to be emulated.
      </p>
    </section>
        
    <section name="4.3 The ActionMapping Implementation" href="actionmapping">
      
      <p>
        In order to operate successfully, the Struts controller servlet needs
        to know several things about how each request URI should be mapped to an
        appropriate <code>Action</code> class.  The required knowledge has been
        encapsulated in a Java interface named <code>ActionMapping</code>, the most
        important properties are as follows:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li><b>type</b> - Fully qualified Java class name of the
          <code>Action</code> implementation class used by this mapping.</li>
        <li><b>name</b> - The name of the form bean defined in the config file
          that this action will use</li>
        <li><b>path</b> - The request URI path that is matched to select this
            mapping.  See below for examples of how matching works.</li>
        <li><b>unknown</b> - Set to <code>true</code> if this action
          should be configured as the default for this application, to handle
          all requests not handled by another action.  Only one action can be
          defined as a default within a single application.</li>
        <li><b>validate</b> - Set to <code>true</code> if the
          <code>validate()</code> method of the action associated
          with this mapping should be called.</li>
        <li><b>forward</b> - The request URI path to which control is passed 
         when his mapping is invoked. This is an alternative to declaring 
         a <b>type</b> property. </li>

      </ul>
               
    </section>
    
    <section name="4.4 The Action Mappings Configuration File" href="config">
      
      <p>
        How does the controller servlet learn about the mappings you want?  It
        would be possible (but tedious) to write a small Java class that simply
        instantiated new <code>ActionMapping</code> instances, and called all of
        the appropriate setter methods.  To make this process easier, Struts includes
        a Digester module that is capable of reading an XML-based description of
        the desired mappings, creating the appropriate objects along the way.
        See the <a href="../api/index.html">API documentation</a> for more information
        about Digester.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        The developer's responsibility is to create an XML file named
        <code>struts-config.xml</code>, and place it in the WEB-INF directory of your
        application. This format of this document is constrained by it's definition in 
        "struts-config_1_0.dtd".  The outermost XML element must be <code>&lt;struts-config&gt;</code>.       
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Inside of the &lt;struts-config&gt; element, there are two important
        elements that are used to describe your actions:
        
        <blockquote>
          <b>&lt;form-beans&gt;</b><br />
            This section contains your form bean definitions.  You use a &lt;form-bean&gt; element
            for each form bean, which has the following important attributes:
            <ul>
              <li>
                <b>name</b>: A unique identifier for this bean, which will be used
                to reference it in corresponding action mappings. Usually, this
                is also the name of the request or session attribute under which
                this form bean will be stored.
              </li>
              <li>
                <b>type</b>: The fully-qualified Java classname of your form bean.
              </li>
            </ul>
        </blockquote>
        <blockquote>
          <b>&lt;action-mappings&gt;</b><br />
            This section contains your action definitions.  You use an &lt;action&gt; element
            for each of your actions you would like to define.  Each action element requires
            the following attributes to be defined:
            
            <ul>
              <li>
                <b>path</b>: The application context-relative path to the action
              </li>
              <li>
                <b>type</b>: The fully qualified java classname of your Action class
              </li>
              <li>
                <b>name</b>: The name of your &lt;form-bean&gt; element to use with this action
              </li>
            </ul>
          </blockquote>
        
      </p>
        

      <p>
        For every &lt;form-bean&gt; tag in your <code>struts-config.xml</code>
        file, you must have a corresponding Java class. The same holds true for
        each &lt;action-mapping&gt; tag.
      </p>

      <p>
        The <code>struts-config.xml</code> file from the example application includes
        the following mapping entry for the "log on" function, which we will use
        to illustrate the requirements.  Note that the entries for all the other actions
        are left out:
      </p>

<pre>
&lt;struts-config>
  &lt;form-beans>
    &lt;form-bean
      name="logonForm"
      type="org.apache.struts.example.LogonForm" />
  &lt;/form-beans>      
  &lt;global-forwards
      type="org.apache.struts.action.ActionForward" />
    &lt;forward name="logon" path="/logon.jsp"
         redirect="false" /> 
  &lt;/global-forwards>      
  &lt;action-mappings&gt;     
    &lt;action
        path="/logon" 
        type="org.apache.struts.example.LogonAction"
        name="logonForm"
       scope="request"
       input="/logon.jsp"
     unknown="false"
    validate="true" />          
  &lt;/action-mappings&gt;
&lt;/struts-config>
</pre>      

      <p>
        First the form bean is defined.  A basic bean of class "<code>org.apache.struts.example.LogonForm</code>"
        is mapped to the logical name "<code>logonForm</code>".  This name is used as a session or request attribute
        name for the form bean.
      </p>
      <p>
        The "<code>global-forwards</code>" section is used to create logical name mappings for commonly used
        jsp pages.  Each of these forwards is available through a call to your action mapping instance,
        i.e. <code>actionMappingInstace.findForward("logicalName")</code>.
      </p>
      <p>
        As you can see, this mapping matches the path <code>/logon</code> (actually,
        because the example application uses extension mapping, the request URI you
        specify in a JSP page would end in <code>/logon.do</code>).  When a request
        that matches this path is received, an instance of the <code>LogonAction</code>
        class will be created (the first time only) and used.  The controller servlet
        will look for a session scoped bean under key <code>logonForm</code>, creating
        and saving a bean of the specified class if needed.
      </p>
      <p>
        Optional but very useful are the local "<code>forward</code>" elements. In the example 
        application, many actions include a local "success" and/or "failure" forward as 
        part of an Action mapping. 
      </p>
<pre>
&lt;!-- Edit mail subscription -->
&lt;action    path="/editSubscription"
  type="org.apache.struts.example.EditSubscriptionAction"
  name="subscriptionForm"
  scope="request"
  validate="false">
  &lt;forward name="failure" path="/mainMenu.jsp"/>
  &lt;forward name="success" path="/subscription.jsp"/>
  &lt;/action>
</pre>   

      <p>Using just these two extra properties, the <code>Action</code> classes in the example 
        application are almost totally independent of the actual names of the JSP pages 
        that are used by the page designers. The pages can be renamed (for example) during 
        a redesign, with negligible impact on the <code>Action</code> classes themselves.  
        If the names of the "next" JSP pages were hard coded into the <code>Action</code> 
        classes, all of these classes would also need to be modified. Of course, you can define
        whatever local forward properties makes sense for your own application.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        One more section of good use is the <code>&lt;data-sources></code> section, which 
        specifies data sources that your application can use.This is how you would specify a basic data source for your application inside
        of struts-config.xml:
      </p>

<pre>
&lt;struts-config>
  &lt;data-sources>
    &lt;data-source
      autoCommit="false"
     description="Example Data Source Description"
     driverClass="org.postgresql.Driver"
        maxCount="4"
        minCount="2"
        password="mypassword"
             url="jdbc:postgresql://localhost/mydatabase"
            user="myusername"/>
  &lt;/data-sources>
&lt;/struts-config>
</pre>

      <p>
        For information on how to retrieve the data source, see the 
        <a href="building_model.html#databases">Accessing Relational Databases</a> section.  
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="4.5 The Web Application Deployment Descriptor" href="dd_config">
      
      <p>
        The final step in setting up the application is to configure the application
        deployment descriptor (stored in file <code>WEB-INF/web.xml</code>) to include
        all the Struts components that are required.  Using the deployment descriptor
        for the example application as a guide, we see that the following entries need
        to be created or modified.
      </p>
      
      <section name="4.5.1 Configure the Action Servlet Instance" href="dd_config_servlet">
        
        <p>
          Add an entry defining the action servlet itself, along with the appropriate
          initialization parameters.  Such an entry might look like this:
        </p>

<pre>
&lt;servlet&gt;
  &lt;servlet-name&gt;action&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
  &lt;servlet-class&gt;
    org.apache.struts.action.ActionServlet
  &lt;/servlet-class&gt;
  &lt;init-param&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;application&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;
      org.apache.struts.example.ApplicationResources
    &lt;/param-value&gt;
  &lt;/init-param&gt;
  &lt;init-param&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;config&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;
      /WEB-INF/struts-config.xml
    &lt;/param-value&gt;
  &lt;/init-param&gt;
  &lt;init-param&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;debug&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;2&lt;/param-value&gt;
  &lt;/init-param&gt;
  &lt;init-param&gt;
    &lt;param-name&gt;mapping&lt;/param-name&gt;
    &lt;param-value&gt;
      org.apache.struts.example.ApplicationMapping
    &lt;/param-value&gt;
  &lt;/init-param&gt;
  &lt;load-on-startup&gt;2&lt;/load-on-startup&gt;
&lt;/servlet&gt;
</pre>
        
        <p>
          The initialization parameters supported by the controller servlet are
          described below. (You can also find these details in the <a 
          href="../api/index.html">Javadocs</a> for the ActionServlet class.) Square brackets 
          describe the default values that are assumed if you do not provide a value for 
          that initialization parameter.
        </p>
        <ul>
  
          <li><strong>application</strong> - Java class name of the application
               resources bundle base class.  [NONE]</li>
          <li><strong>bufferSize</strong> - The size of the input buffer used when
               processing file uploads.  [4096]</li>
          <li><strong>config</strong> - Context-relative path to the XML resource
              containing our configuration information.
              [/WEB-INF/struts-config.xml]</li>
          <li><strong>content</strong> - Default content type and character encoding
              to be set on each response; may be overridden by a forwarded-to
              servlet or JSP page.  [text/html]</li>
          <li><strong>debug</strong> - The debugging detail level for this
              servlet, which controls how much information is logged.  [0]</li>
          <li><strong>detail</strong> - The debugging detail level for the Digester
              we utilize in <code>initMapping()</code>, which logs to System.out
              instead of the servlet log.  [0]</li>
          <li><strong>factory</strong> - The Java class name of the
              <code>MessageResourcesFactory</code> used to create the application
              <code>MessageResources</code> object.
              [org.apache.struts.util.PropertyMessageResourcesFactory]</li>
          <li><strong>formBean</strong> - The Java class name of the ActionFormBean
              implementation to use [org.apache.struts.action.ActionFormBean].</li>
          <li><strong>forward</strong> - The Java class name of the ActionForward
              implementation to use [org.apache.struts.action.ActionForward].
              Two convenient classes you may wish to use are:
              <ul>
              <li><em>org.apache.struts.action.ForwardingActionForward</em> -
                  Subclass of <code>org.apache.struts.action.ActionForward</code>
                  that defaults the <code>redirect</code> property to
                  <code>false</code> (same as the ActionForward default value).</li>
              <li><em>org.apache.struts.action.RedirectingActionForward</em> -
                  Subclass of <code>org.apache.struts.action.ActionForward</code>
                  that defaults the <code>redirect</code> property to
                  <code>true</code>.</li>
              </ul></li>
          <li><strong>locale</strong> - If set to <code>true</code>, and there is a
              user session, identify and store an appropriate
              <code>java.util.Locale</code> object (under the standard key
              identified by <code>Action.LOCALE_KEY</code>) in the user's session
              if there is not a Locale object there already. [true]</li>
          <li><strong>mapping</strong> - The Java class name of the ActionMapping
              implementation to use [org.apache.struts.action.ActionMapping].
              Two convenient classes you may wish to use are:
              <ul>
              <li><em>org.apache.struts.action.RequestActionMapping</em> - Subclass
                  of <code>org.apache.struts.action.ActionMapping</code> that
                  defaults the <code>scope</code> property to "request".</li>
              <li><em>org.apache.struts.action.SessionActionMapping</em> - Subclass
                  of <code>org.apache.struts.action.ActionMapping</code> that
                  defaults the <code>scope</code> property to "session".  (Same
                  as the ActionMapping default value).</li>
              </ul></li>
          <li><strong>maxFileSize</strong> - The maximum size (in bytes) of a file
              to be accepted as a file upload.  Can be expressed as a number followed
              by a "K" "M", or "G", which are interpreted to mean kilobytes,
              megabytes, or gigabytes, respectively.  [250M]</li>
          <li><strong>multipartClass</strong> - The fully qualified name of the
              MultipartRequestHandler implementation class to be used for processing
              file uploads.  [org.apache.struts.upload.DiskMultipartRequestHandler]
              </li>
          <li><strong>nocache</strong> - If set to <code>true</code>, add HTTP headers
              to every response intended to defeat browser caching of any response we
              generate or forward to.  [false]</li>
          <li><strong>null</strong> - If set to <code>true</code>, set our application
              resources to return <code>null</code> if an unknown message key is used.
              Otherwise, an error message including the offending message key will
              be returned.  [true]</li>
          <li><strong>tempDir</strong> - The temporary working directory to use when
              processing file uploads.  [The working directory provided to this web
              application as a servlet context attribute]</li>
          <li><strong>validate</strong> - Are we using the new configuration file
              format?  [true]</li>  
          <li><strong>validating</strong> - Should we use a validating XML parse to
              process the configuration file (strongly recommended)? [true]</li>  
        </ul>
      </section>
      
      <section name="4.5.2 Configure the Action Servlet Mapping" href="dd_config_mapping">
      
        <p>
          <strong>Note:</strong> The material in this section is not specific to
          Struts. The configuration of servlet mappings is defined in the Java
          Servlet Specification. This section describes the most common means
          of configuring a Struts application.
        </p>
        <p>
          There are two common approaches to defining the URLs that will
          be processed by the controller servlet -- prefix matching and extension
          matching.  An appropriate mapping entry for each approach will be
          described below.
        </p>
          
        <p>
          Prefix matching means that you want all URLs that start (after the context
          path part) with a particular value to be passed to this servlet.  Such an
          entry might look like this:
        </p>

<pre>
  &lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
     &lt;servlet-name&gt;action&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
     &lt;url-pattern&gt;/execute/*&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
   &lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;
</pre>
        
        <p>
          which means that a request URI to match the <code>/logon</code> path
          described earlier might look like this:</p>

<pre>
http://www.mycompany.com/myapplication/execute/logon
</pre>

        <p>
          where <code>/myapplication</code> is the context path under which your
          application is deployed.
        </p>
          
        <p>
          Extension mapping, on the other hand, matches request URIs to the action
          servlet based on the fact that the URI ends with a period followed by a
          defined set of characters.  For example, the JSP processing servlet is mapped
          to the <code>*.jsp</code> pattern so that it is called to process every
          JSP page that is requested.  To use the <code>*.do</code> extension (which
          implies "do something"), the mapping entry would look like this:
        </p>

<pre>
  &lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
     &lt;servlet-name&gt;action&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
     &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.do&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
   &lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;
</pre>
        
        <p>
          and a request URI to match the <code>/logon</code> path described
          earlier might look like this:
        </p>

<pre>
http://www.mycompany.com/myapplication/logon.do
</pre>
      </section>
      
      <section name="4.5.3 Configure the Struts Tag Library" href="dd_config_taglib">
        
        <p>
          Next, you must add an entry defining the Struts tag library.  There are currently four
          taglibs that Struts is packaged with.
        </p>
        <p>
          The struts-bean taglib contains tags useful in accessing
          beans and their properties, as well as defining new beans (based on these accesses) that are
          accessible to the remainder of the page via scripting variables and page scope attributes.
          Convenient mechanisms to create new beans based on the value of request cookies, headers, 
          and parameters are also provided.
        </p>
        <p>
          The struts-html taglib contains tags used to create struts input forms, as well as other
          tags generally useful in the creation of HTML-based user interfaces.
        </p>
        <p>
          The struts-logic taglib contains tags that are useful in managing conditional generation
          of output text, looping over object collections for repetitive generation of output text,
          and application flow management.
        </p>
        <p>
          The struts-template taglib contains tags that define a template mechanism.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          Below is how you would define all taglibs for use within your application,
          in reality you would only specify the taglib's that your application will use:
        </p>

<pre>
&lt;taglib&gt;
  &lt;taglib-uri&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-bean.tld
  &lt;/taglib-uri&gt;
  &lt;taglib-location&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-bean.tld
  &lt;/taglib-location&gt;
&lt;/taglib&gt;
&lt;taglib&gt;
  &lt;taglib-uri&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-html.tld
  &lt;/taglib-uri&gt;
  &lt;taglib-location&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-html.tld
  &lt;/taglib-location&gt;
&lt;/taglib&gt;
&lt;taglib&gt;
  &lt;taglib-uri&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-logic.tld
  &lt;/taglib-uri&gt;
  &lt;taglib-location&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-logic.tld
  &lt;/taglib-location&gt;
&lt;/taglib&gt;
&lt;taglib&gt;
  &lt;taglib-uri&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-template.tld
  &lt;/taglib-uri&gt;
  &lt;taglib-location&gt;
    /WEB-INF/struts-template.tld
  &lt;/taglib-location&gt;
&lt;/taglib&gt;
</pre>

        <p>
          This tells the JSP system where to find the tag library descriptor
          for this library (in your application's WEB-INF directory, instead of
          out on the Internet somewhere).
        </p>
      </section>
      
      <section name="4.5.4 Add Struts Components To Your Application" href="config_add">
        
        <p>
         To use Struts, you must copy the .tld files that you require into
         your <code>WEB-INF</code> directory, and copy <code>struts.jar</code>
         (and all of the <code>commons-*.jar</code> files) into your
         <code>WEB-INF/lib</code> directory.
        </p>
                                <p>
                                        Next: <a href="resources.html">Struts Resources</a>
                                </p>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  </body>
</document>
