<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./building_view.xml">

  <properties>
    <author>Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author>Mike Schachter</author>
    <author>Ted Husted</author>
    <author>Martin Cooper</author>
    <author>Ed Burns</author>
    <title>The Struts User's Guide - Building View Components</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>  
  <chapter name="3. Building View Components" href="building_view">
  
      <section name="3.1 Overview" href="overview">
        
        <p>
          This chapter focuses on the task of building the <i>View</i> components
        of the application, which will primarily be created using JavaServer Pages
        (JSP) technology.  In particular, Struts provides support for building
        internationalized applications, as well as for interacting with input forms.
        Several other topics related to the View components are briefly discussed.
      </p>
      
    </section>
    
    <section name="3.2 Internationalized Messages" href="i18n">
      
      <p>
        A few years ago, application developers could count on having to support
        only residents of their own country, who are used to only one (or sometimes
        two) languages, and one way to represent numeric quantities like dates,
        numbers, and monetary values.  However, the explosion of application
        development based on web technologies, as well as the deployment of such
        applications on the Internet and other broadly accessible networks, have
        rendered national boundaries invisible in many cases.  This has translated
        (if you will pardon the pun) into a need for applications to support
        <i>internationalization</i> (often called "i18n" because 18 is the number of
        letters in between the "i" and the "n") and <i>localization</i>.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        Struts builds upon the Java platform to provide assistance
        for building internationalized and localized applications.  The key concepts
        to become familiar with are:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li><b>Locale</b> - The fundamental Java class that supports
            internationalization is <code>java.util.Locale</code>.  Each
            <code>Locale</code> represents a particular choice of country and
            language (plus an optional language variant), and also a set of
            formatting assumptions for things like numbers and dates.</li>
        <li><b>ResourceBundle</b> - The <code>java.util.ResourceBundle</code> class
            provides the fundmental tools for supporting messages in multiple
            languages.  See the Javadocs for the <code>ResourceBundle</code> class,
            and the information on Internationalization in the documentation bundle
            for your JDK release, for more information.</li>
        <li><b>PropertyResourceBundle</b> - One of the standard implementations of
            <code>ResourceBundle</code> allows you to define resources using the
            same "name=value" syntax used to initialize properties files.  This is
            very convenient for preparing resource bundles with messages that are
            used in a web application, because these messages are generally text
            oriented.</li>
        <li><b>MessageFormat</b> - The <code>java.text.MessageFormat</code> class
            allows you to replace portions of a message string (in this case,
            one retrieved from a resource bundle) with arguments specified at
            run time.  This is useful in cases where you are creating a sentence,
            but the words would appear in a different order in different languages.
            The placeholder string <code>{0}</code> in the message is replaced by
            the first runtime argument, <code>{1}</code> is replaced by the second
            argument, and so on.</li>
        <li><b>MessageResources</b> - The Struts class
            <code><a href="api/org/apache/struts/util/MessageResources.html">org.apache.struts.util.MessageResources</a></code> lets you treat
            a set of resource bundles like a database, and allows you to request
            a particular message string for a particular Locale (normally one
            associated with the current user) instead of for the default Locale
            the server itself is running in.</li>
      </ul>
        
      <p>
        Please note that the i18n support in a framework like Struts is limited to the
        <b>presentation</b> of internationalized text and images to the user.
        Support for Locale specific <b>input methods</b> (used with languages 
        such as Japanese, Chinese, and Korean) is left up to the client device, which 
        is usually a web browser.
      </p>

      <p>
        For an internationalized application, follow the steps described in
        the Internationalization document in the JDK documentation bundle for your
        platform to create a properties file containing the messages for each
        language.  An example will illustrate this further:
      </p>
        
      <p>
        Assume that your source code is created in package
        <code>com.mycompany.mypackage</code>, so it is stored in a directory
        (relative to your source directory) named
        <code>com/mycompany/mypackage</code>.  To create a resource bundle called
        <code>com.mycompany.mypackage.MyResources</code>, you would create the
        following files in the <code>com/mycompany/mypackage</code> directory:
      </p>
    
      <ul>
        <li><b>MyResources.properties</b> - Contains the messages in the default
            language for your server.  If your default language is English, you
            might have an entry like this:
            <code>prompt.hello=Hello</code></li>
        <li><b>MyResources_xx.properties</b> - Contains the same messages in the
            language whose ISO language code is "xx" (See the ResourceBundle
            Javadoc page for a link to the current list).  For a French version
            of the message shown above, you would have this entry:
            <code>prompt.hello=Bonjour</code>
            You can have resource bundle files for as many languages as you need.</li>
      </ul>
        
      <p>
        When you configure the controller servlet in the web application
        deployment descriptor, one of the things you will need to define in
        an initialization parameter is the base name of the resource bundle
        for the application.  In the case described above, it would be
        <code>com.mycompany.mypackage.MyResources</code>. 
      </p>
<pre>
&lt;servlet>
  &lt;servlet-name>action&lt;/servlet-name>
  &lt;servlet-class>org.apache.struts.action.ActionServlet&lt;/servlet-class>
  &lt;init-param>
    &lt;param-name>application&lt;/param-name>
    &lt;param-value>com.mycompany.mypackage.MyResources&lt;/param-value>
  &lt;/init-param>
  &lt;.../>
&lt;/servlet>
</pre>
     
      <p>
        The important thing is for the resource bundle to be found on the 
        class path for your application. Another approach is to store 
        the <code>MyResources.properties</code> file in your application's 
        <code>classes</code> folder. You can then simply specify "myResources" as the 
        application value. Just be careful it is not deleted if your 
        build script deletes classes as part of a "clean" target.
      </p>
      <p>
        If it does, here is an Ant task to run when compiling your application 
        that copies the contents of a <code>src/conf</code>
        directory to the <code>classes</code> directory:
      </p>
       <pre>
        &lt;!-- Copy any configuration files -->
        &lt;copy todir="classes">
            &lt;fileset dir="src/conf"/>
        &lt;/copy>
       </pre>
    </section>

    <section name="3.3 Forms and FormBean Interactions" href="form_beans">    
      <p>
        At one time or another, most web developers have built forms using
        the standard capabilities of HTML, such as the <code>&lt;input&gt;</code>
        tag.  Users have come to expect interactive applications to have certain
        behaviors, and one of these expectations relates to error handling -- if
        the user makes an error, the application should allow them to fix just what
        needs to be changed -- without having to re-enter any of the rest of the
        information on the current page or form.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        Fulfilling this expectation is tedious and cumbersome when coding with
        standard HTML and JSP pages.  For example, an input element for a
        <code>username</code> field might look like this (in JSP):
       </p>
      
<pre>
&lt;input type="text" name="username"
      value="&lt;%= loginBean.getUsername() %&gt;"/&gt;
</pre>
      
      <p>
        which is difficult to type correctly, confuses HTML developers who are
        not knowledgeable about programming concepts, and can cause problems with
        HTML editors.  Instead, Struts provides a comprehensive facility for
        building forms, based on the Custom Tag Library facility of JSP 1.1.
        The case above would be rendered like this using Struts:
      </p>

<pre>
&lt;html:text property="username"/&gt;
</pre>

      <p> 
        with no need to explicitly refer to the JavaBean from which the initial
        value is retrieved.  That is handled automatically by the framework.
      </p>
      <p>
        HTML forms are sometimes used to upload other files. Most browsers 
        support this through a &lt;input type="file"&gt; element, that generates 
        a file browse button, but it's up to the developer to handle the incoming
        files. Struts handles these "multipart" forms in a way identical to 
        building normal forms. In the next section, we will cover using Struts to 
        create a simple login form, and also a simple mulitpart form. 
      </p>   
      </section>

      <section name="3.3.1 Building Forms With Struts" href="forms">
        
        <p>
          A complete example of a login form will illustrate how Struts
          makes dealing with forms much less painful than using straight HTML
          and standard JSP facilities.  Consider the following page (based on the
          example application included with Struts) named <code>logon.jsp</code>:
        </p>       
<hr/>
<pre>
&lt;%@ page language="java" %&gt;
&lt;%@ taglib uri="/WEB-INF/struts-html.tld"
        prefix="html" %&gt;
&lt;%@ taglib uri="/WEB-INF/struts-bean.tld"
        prefix="bean" %&gt;
&lt;html:html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;title&gt;
  &lt;bean:message key="logon.title"/&gt;
&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;body bgcolor="white"&gt;
&lt;html:errors/&gt;
&lt;html:form action="/logon" focus="username"&gt;
&lt;table border="0" width="100%"&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th align="right"&gt;
      &lt;bean:message key="prompt.username"/&gt;
    &lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td align="left"&gt;
      &lt;html:text property="username"
                     size="16"/&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th align="right"&gt;
      &lt;bean:message key="prompt.password"/&gt;
    &lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;td align="left"&gt;
      &lt;html:password property="password"
                         size="16"/&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td align="right"&gt;
      &lt;html:submit&gt;
        &lt;bean:message key="button.submit"/&gt;
      &lt;/html:submit&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td align="right"&gt;
      &lt;html:reset&gt;
        &lt;bean:message key="button.reset"/&gt;
      &lt;/html:reset&gt;
    &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/html:form&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html:html&gt;
</pre>
<hr/>
        <p>
          The following items illustrate the key features of form handling in Struts,
          based on this example:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>The <code>taglib</code> directive tells the JSP page compiler where to
              find the <i>tag library descriptor</i> for the Struts tag library.  In
              this case, we are using <code>bean</code> as the prefix that identifies
              tags from the struts-bean library, and "html" as the prefix that identifies
              tags from the struts-html library.  Any desired prefix can be used.</li>
          <li>This page uses several occurrences of the
              message tag to look up internationalized
              message strings from a <code>MessageResources</code> object containing
              all the resources for this application.  For this page to work, the
              following message keys must be defined in these resources:
              <ul>
                <li><b>logon.title</b> - Title of the logon page</li>
                <li><b>prompt.username</b> - A "Username:" prompt string</li>
                <li><b>prompt.password</b> - A "Password:" prompt string</li>
                <li><b>button.submit</b> - "Submit" for the button label</li>
                <li><b>button.reset</b> - "Reset" for the button label</li>
              </ul>
              When the user logs on, the application can store a <code>Locale</code>
              object in the user's session.  This <code>Locale</code> will be used
              to select messages in the appropriate language.  This makes it easy to
              implement giving the user an option to switch languages -- simply change
              the stored <code>Locale</code> object, and all messages are switched
              automatically.</li>
          <li>The errors tag displays any error
              messages that have been stored by a business logic component, or nothing
              if no errors have been stored.  This tag will be described further
              below.</li>
          <li>The form tag renders an HTML
              <code>&lt;form&gt;</code> element, based on the specified attributes.
              It also associates all of the fields within this form with a session
              scoped FormBean that is stored under the key <code>logonForm</code>.
              The Struts developer provides the Java implementation of this form
              bean, subclassing the Struts class <code>ActionForm</code>.
              This bean is used to provide initial values for all of the input
              fields that have names matching the property names of the bean.
              If an appropriate bean is not found, a new one will be created
              automatically, using the specified Java class name.
              <li>The form bean can also be specified in the Struts configuration file, 
              in which case the Name and Type can be omitted 
              here. See "<a href="building_controller.html#config">The Action Mappings 
              Configuration File</a>" for details.)</li>
              </li>
          <li>The text tag renders an HTML
              <code>&lt;input&gt;</code> element of type "text".  In this case,
              the number of character positions to occupy on the browser's screen
              has been specified as well.  When this page is executed, the current
              value of the <code>username</code> property of the corresponding bean
              (that is, the value returned by <code>getUsername()</code>).</li>
          <li>The password tag is used similarly.
              The difference is that the browser will echo asterisk characters,
              instead of the input value, as the user types their password.</li>.
          <li>The submit and
              reset tags generate the corresponding
              buttons at the bottom of the form.  The text labels for each button
              are created using message tags,
              as with the prompts, so that these values are internationalized.</li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>
          Handling multipart forms is also easy.  Obviously when you create a multipart
          form you're creating a form that has at least one input of type "file".  The first step to
          creating a multipart form is to utilize the struts-html taglib to create the presentation
          page:
        </p>

<hr/>          
<pre>
&lt;%@page language="java">
&lt;%@taglib uri="/WEB-INF/struts-html.tld"
       prefix="html">
&lt;html:form action="uploadAction.do" enctype="multipart/form-data">
  Please Input Text:
  &lt;html:text property="myText">&lt;br/>
  Please Input The File You Wish to Upload:&lt;br/>
  &lt;html:file property="myFile">&lt;br />
  &lt;html:submit />
&lt;/html:form>
</pre>
<hr/>
        <p>
          The next step is to create your ActionForm bean:
        </p>

<hr/>
<pre>
import javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest;
import javax.servlet.http.HttpServletResponse;
import org.apache.struts.action.ActionForm;
import org.apache.struts.action.ActionMapping;
import org.apache.struts.upload.FormFile;
public class UploadForm extends ActionForm {
  protected String myText;
  protected FormFile myFile;
  public void setMyText(String text) {
    myText = text;
  }
  public String getMyText() {
    return myText;
  }
  public void setMyFile(FormFile file) {
    myFile = file;
  }
  public FormFile getMyFile() {
    return myFile;
  }
}
</pre>
<hr/>        
        <p>
          Look at the <a href="../api/index.html">Javadocs</a> for FormFile to see the
          methods it exposes to manipulate files in file uploading.  Also look at the
          Javadocs for ActionServlet and ActionMapping for the various parameters
          you can specify to change how files are uploaded.  Basically in your
          peform() method in your action class you would call <code>((UploadForm) form).getMyFile()</code>
          to retrieve the FormFile and do what you want with it.
        </p>        
              
      </section>
      
      <section name="3.3.2 Input Field Types Supported" href="form_input">
        
        <p>
          Struts defines HTML tags for all of the following types of input fields,
          with hyperlinks to the corresponding reference information.
        </p>
        
        <ul>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#checkbox">checkboxes</a></li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#hidden">hidden</a> fields</li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#password">password</a> input fields</li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#radio">radio</a> buttons</li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#reset">reset</a> buttons</li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#select">select</a> lists with embedded option or options items</li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#option">option</a></li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#options">options</a></li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#submit">submit</a> buttons</li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#text">text</a> input fields</li>
            <li><a href="../struts-html.html#textarea">textareas</a></li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>
          In every
          case, a field tag must be nested within a <code>form</code> tag, so that
          the field knows what bean to use for initializing displayed values.
        </p>
      </section>
      
      <section name="3.3.3 Other Useful Presentation Tags" href="presentation_tags">
        
        <p>
          There are several tags useful for creating presentations, consult the documentation
          on each specific tag library, along with the Tag Developers Guides, for more 
          information:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
       
          <li>[logic] <a href="../struts-logic.html#iterate">iterate</a> repeats its tag body once
              for each element of a specified collection (which can be an Enumeration,
              a Hashtable, a Vector, or an array of objects).</li>
          <li>[logic] <a href="../struts-logic.html#present">present</a> depending on which attribute
              is specified, this tag checks the current request, and evaluates the nested 
              body content of this tag only if the specified value is present. Only one of 
              the attributes may be used in one occurrence of this tag, unless you use the
              property attribute, in which case the name attribute is also required. The 
              attributes include cookie, header, name, parameter, property, role, scope, 
              and user.
          </li>
          <li>[logic] <a href="../struts-logic.html#notPresent">notPresent</a> the companion tag to 
              present, notPresent provides the same functionality when the specified attribute
              is not present.</li>        
          <li>[html] <a href="../struts-html.html#link">link</a> generates a HTML &lt;a&gt; element 
              as an anchor definition or a hyperlink to the specified URL, and automatically
              applies URL encoding to maintain session state in the absence of
              cookie support.</li>
          <li>[html] <a href="../struts-html.html#img">img</a> generates a HTML &lt;img&gt; element 
              with the ability to dynamically modify the URLs specified by the "src" and 
              "lowsrc" attributes in the same manner that &lt;html:link> can.
         </li>  
          <li>[bean] <a href="../struts-bean.html#parameter">parameter</a> retrieves the value of the 
              specified request parameter, and defines the result as a page scope attribute of
              type String or String[].</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      
      <section name="3.3.4 Automatic Form Validation" href="form_validation">    
     
        <p>
          In addition to the form and bean interactions described above, Struts
          offers an additional facility to validate the input fields it has received.
          To utilize this feature, override the following method in your ActionForm 
          class:
        </p>

<pre>public ActionErrors
  validate(ActionMapping mapping,
    HttpServletRequest request);
</pre>
        
        <p>
          The validate() method is called by the controller servlet after the bean
          properties have been populated, but before the corresponding action class's
          <code>perform()</code> method is invoked. The <code>validate()</code> method
          has the following options:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>Perform the appropriate validations and find no problems -- Return either
              <code>null</code> or a zero-length ActionErrors instance, and the controller 
              servlet will proceed to call the <code>perform()</code> method of the 
              appropriate <code>Action</code> class.</li>
          <li>Perform the appropriate validations and find problems -- Return an ActionErrors
              instance containing <code>ActionError</code>'s, which are classes that contain
              the error message keys (into the application's
              <code>MessageResources</code> bundle) that should be displayed. The
              controller servlet will store this array as a request attribute suitable
              for use by the <code>&lt;html:errors&gt;</code> tag, and will forward
              control back to the input form (identified by the <code>input</code>
              property for this <code>ActionMapping</code>).</li>
        </ul>
          
        <p>
          As mentioned earlier, this feature is entirely optional.  The default implementation
          of the validate() method returns <code>null</code>, and the controller servlet
          will assume that any required validation is done by the action class.
        </p>
        <p>
          One common approach is to perform simple, prima facia validations using the 
          ActionForm validate() method, and then handle the "business logic" validation 
          from the Action. 
        </p>
        <p>
          An optional package for performing ActionForm validations is available in the 
          Nightly Build and from <a href="http://home.earthlink.net/~dwinterfeldt/">
          David Winterfeldt's Web site</a>.
        </p>
      </section>
    
    <section name="3.4 Other Presentation Techniques" href="other_presentations">
    
      <p>
        Although the look and feel of your application can be completely constructed
        based on the standard capabilities of JSP and the Struts custom tag library,
        you should consider employing other techniques that will improve component
        reuse, reduce maintenance efforts, and/or reduce errors.  Several options
        are discussed in the following sections.
      </p>
    </section>
      
      <section name="3.4.1 Application-Specific Custom Tags" href="custom_tags">
      
        <p>
          Beyond using the custom tags provided by the Struts library, it is easy
          to create tags that are specific to the application you are building, to
          assist in creating the user interface.  The example application included with
          Struts illustrates this principle by creating the following tags unique to
          the implementation of this application:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
          <li><b>checkLogon</b> - Checks for the existence of a particular session
              object, and forwards control to the logon page if it is missing.  This is
              used to catch cases where a user has bookmarked a page in the middle of
              your application and tries to bypass logging on, or if the user's session
              has been timed out.</li>
          <li><b>linkSubscription</b> - Generates a hyperlink to a details page
              for a Subscription, which passes the required primary key values as
              request attributes.  This is used when listing the subscriptions associated
              with a user, and providing links to edit or delete them.</li>
          <li><b>linkUser</b> - Generates a hyperlink to a details page
              for a User, which passes the required primary key values as
              request attributes.</li>
        </ul>
          
        <p>
          The source code for these tags is in the <code>src/example</code> directory,
          in package <code>org.apache.struts.example</code>, along with the other Java
          classes that are used in this application.
        </p>
      </section>
      
      <section name="3.4.2 Page Composition With Includes" href="includes">
        
        <p>
          Creating the entire presentation of a page in one JSP file (with custom
          tags and beans to access the required dynamic data) is a very common design
          approach, and was employed in the example application included with Struts.
          However, many applications require the display of multiple logically distinct
          portions of your application together on a single page.</p>
          
        <p>
          For example, a portal application might have some or all of the following
          functional capabilities available on the portal's "home" page:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>Access to a search engine for this portal.</li>
          <li>One or more "news feed" displays, with the topics of interest customized
              from the user's registration profile.</li>
          <li>Access to discussion topics related to this portal.</li>
          <li>A "mail waiting" indicator if your portal provides free email
              accounts.</li>
        </ul>
          
        <p>
          The development of the various segments of this site is easier if you
          can divide up the work, and assign different developers to the different
          segments.  Then, you can use the <i>include</i> capability of JavaServer Pages
          technology to combine the results into a single result page, or use the include tag
          provided with Struts.  There are three
          types of <i>include</i> available, depending on when you want the combination
          of output to occur:
        </p>
          
        <ul>
          <li>An <code>&lt;%@ include file="xxxxx" %&gt;</code> directive can include a file that contains
          Java code or JSP tags. The code in the included file can even reference
          variables declared earlier in the outer jsp page. The code is inlined into
          the other JavaServer Page before it is compiled so it can definately contain more than
          just HTML.</li>
          <li>The include <i>action</i> (<code>&lt;jsp:include page="xxxxx"
              flush="true" /&gt;</code>) is processed at request time, and is handled
              transparently by the server.  Among other things, that means you
              can conditionally perform the include by nesting it within a tag
              like <a href="../struts-logic.html#equals">equals</a> by using it's
              parameter attribute.</li>
          <li>The <a href="../struts-bean.html#include">bean:include</a> tag takes either a
             an argument "forward" representing a logical name mapped to the jsp to include,
             or the "id" argument, which represents a page context String variable to print
             out to the jsp page.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
          Another approach to this would be to use the Struts Template Tag library. See the         
          Developer's Guide for details.
        </p>  
        <p>
          Tiles is an alternative to the original Template Tag library, offering several 
          enhancements and new capabilities. Tiles is available in the 
          Nightly Build, and from <a href="http://www.lifl.fr/~dumoulin/tiles/">
          Cedric Dumoulin's Web site</a>.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section name="3.4.3 Image Rendering Components" href="image_rendering">
      
        <p>
          Some applications require dynamically generated images, like the price
          charts on a stock reporting site.  Two different approaches are commonly used
          to meet these requirements:
        </p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>Render a hyperlink with a URL that executes a servlet request.  The
              servlet will use a graphics library to render the graphical image,
              set the content type appropriately (such as to <code>image/gif</code>),
              and send back the bytes of that image to the browser, which will display
              them just as if it had received a static file.</li>
          <li>Render the HTML code necessary to download a Java applet that creates
              the required graph.  You can configure the graph by setting appropriate
              initialization parameters for the applet in the rendered code, or you
              can have the applet make its own connection to the server to receive
              these parameters.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section name="3.4.4 Rendering Text" href="text_rendering">

         <p>
           Some applications require dynamically generated text or markup, 
           such as XML. If a complete page is being rendered, and can be output 
           using a PrintWriter, this is very easy to do from an Action:
         </p>
         <pre>
           response.setContentType("text/plain"); // or text/xml
           PrintWriter writer = response.getWriter();
           // use writer to render text
           return(null);
         </pre>

        <p align="center">
          Next: <a href="building_controller.html">Building Controller Components</a>
        </p>
      </section>

  </chapter>
  </body>
</document> 
  



