<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./building_model.xml">

  <properties>
    <author>Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <author>Mike Schachter</author>
    <author>Ted Husted</author>
    <author>Martin Cooper</author>
    <author>Ed Burns</author>
    <title>The Struts User's Guide - Building Model Components</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>  
  <chapter name="2. Building Model Components" href="building_model">
  
      <section name="2.1 Overview" href="overview">
        
        <p>
        Many requirements documents used for building web applications
        focus on the <i>View</i>.  However, you should ensure that the
        processing required for each submitted request is also clearly
        defined from the <i>Model's</i> perspective.  In general, the
        developer of the <i>Model</i> components will be focusing on
        the creation of JavaBeans classes that support all of the
        functional requirements.  The precise nature of the beans
        required by a particular application will vary widely
        depending on those requirements, but they can generally be
        classified into several categories discussed below.  However,
        a brief review of the concept of "scope" as it relates to
        beans and JSP is useful first.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="2.2 JavaBeans and Scope" href="javabeans">
    
      <p>
        Within a web-based application, JavaBeans can be stored in (and accessed
        from) a number of different collections of "attributes".  Each collection
        has different rules for the lifetime of that collection, and the visibility
        of the beans stored there.  Together, the rules defining lifetime and
        visibility are called the <i>scope</i> of those beans.  The JavaServer
        Pages (JSP) Specification defines scope choices using the following terms
        (with the equivalent servlet API concept defined in parentheses):
      </p>
        
      <ul>
        <li><b>page</b> - Beans that are visible within a single JSP page,
            for the lifetime of the current request.  (Local variables of
            the <code>service()</code> method)</li>
        <li><b>request</b> - Beans that are visible within a single JSP page,
            as well as to any page or servlet that is included in this page,
            or forwarded to by this page.  (Request attributes)</li>
        <li><b>session</b> - Beans that are visible to all JSP pages and
            servlets that participate in a particular user session, across one
            or more requests.  (Session attributes)</li>
        <li><b>application</b> - Beans that are visible to all JSP pages and
            servlets that are part of a web application.  (Servlet context
            attributes)</li>
      </ul>
        
      <p>
        It is important to remember that JSP pages and servlets in the same
        web application share the same sets of bean collections.  For example,
        a bean stored as a request attribute in a servlet like this:
      </p>
        
      <p><code>MyCart mycart = new MyCart(...);<br />
        request.setAttribute("cart", mycart);
      </code></p>
      
      <p>
        is immediately visible to a JSP page which this servlet forwards to,
        using a standard action tag like this:
      </p>
        
      <p><code>&lt;jsp:useBean id="cart" scope="request"<br />
        class="com.mycompany.MyApp.MyCart"/&gt;
      </code></p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="2.3 ActionForm Beans" href="actionform">
      
      <p>
        Note: ActionForm beans are actually closer to the <i>View</i>
        than the <i>Model</i>.
      </p>
      <p>
        The Struts framework generally assumes that you have defined an
        <code>ActionForm</code> bean (that is, a Java class extending the
        <code>ActionForm</code> class) for each input form required in your
        application. <code>ActionForm</code> beans are sometimes just called
        "form beans". If you declare such beans in your <code>ActionMapping</code>
        configuration file (see "<a href="building_controller.html#config">
        Building the Controller Components</a>"), the Struts  controller servlet 
        will automatically perform the following services for you, before 
        invoking the appropriate <code>Action</code> method:
      </p>
        
      <ul>
        <li>Check in the user's session for an instance of a bean of the
            appropriate class, under the appropriate key.</li>
        <li>If there is no such session scope bean available, a new one is
            automatically created and added to the user's session.</li>
        <li>For every request parameter whose name corresponds to the name
            of a property in the bean, the corresponding setter method will
            be called.  This operates in a manner similar to the standard
            JSP action <code>&lt;jsp:setProperty&gt;</code> when you use the
            asterisk wildcard to select all properties.</li>
        <li>The updated <code>ActionForm</code> bean will be passed to the
            Action Class <code>perform()</code> method when it is called,
            making these values immediately available.</li>
      </ul>
        
      <p>
        When you code your <code>ActionForm</code> beans, keep the following
        principles in mind:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>The <code>ActionForm</code> class itself requires no specific
            methods to be implemented.  It is used to identify the role these
            particular beans play in the overall architecture.  Typically, an
            <code>ActionForm</code> bean will have only property getter and
            property setter methods, with no business logic.</li>           
            <li>The ActionForm object also offers a standard validation mechanism. 
            If you override a "stub" method, and provide error messages in the 
            standard application resource, Struts will automatically validate the 
            input from the form (using your method). See "<a 
            href="./building_view.html#form_validation">Action Form Validation</a>" 
            for details. Of course, you can also ignore the ActionForm validation 
            and provide your own in the Action object.</li>            
        <li>Define a property (with associated <code>getXxx()</code> and
            <code>setXxx()</code> methods) for each field that is present
            in the form.  The field name and property name must match according
            to the usual JavaBeans conventions.  For example, an input field named
            <code>username</code> will cause the <code>setUsername()</code> method
            to be called.</li>
        <li>Think of your ActionForm beans as a firewall between HTTP and the Action. 
            Use the validate method to ensure all required properties are present, and 
            that they contain reasonable values. An ActionForm that fails validation 
            will not even be presented to the Action for handling.</li>
        <li>You may also place a bean instance on your form, and use nested property 
            references. For example, you might have a "customer" bean on your Action 
            Form, and then refer to the property "customer.name" in your JSP view. 
            This would correspond to the methods <code>customer.getName()</code> and 
            <code>customer.setName(string Name)</code> on your customer bean. See the 
            Tag Library Developer Guides for more about nested syntax.</li>
        <li><i>Caution:</i> If you nest an existing bean instance on your form, think 
            about the properties it exposes. Any public property on an ActionForm that 
            accepts a single String value can be set with a query string. It may be 
            useful to place such beans inside a thin "wrapper" that exposes only the 
            properties required. This wrapper can also provide a filter to be 
            sure runtime properties are not set to inappropriate values.</li> 
      </ul>
        
      <p>
        You should note that a "form", in the sense discussed here, does not
        necessarily correspond to a single JSP page in the user interface.  It is
        common in many applications to have a "form" (from the user's perspective)
        that extends over multiple pages.  Think, for example, of the wizard style
        user interface that is commonly used when installing new applications.  Struts
        encourages you to define a single <code>ActionForm</code> bean that contains
        properties for all of the fields, no matter which page the field is actually
        displayed on.  Likewise, the various pages of the same form should all be
        submitted to the same Action Class.  If you follow these suggestions, the
        page designers can rearrange the fields among the various pages, often without 
        requiring changes to the processing logic.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="2.4 System State Beans" href="system_state">
      
      <p>
        The actual state of a system is normally represented as a set of one or
        more JavaBeans classes, whose properties define the current state.  A
        shopping cart system, for example, will include a bean that represents the
        cart being maintained for each individual shopper, and will (among other
        things) include the set of items that the shopper has currently selected
        for purchase.  Separately, the system will also include different beans
        for the user's profile information (including their credit card and ship-to
        addresses), as well as the catalog of available items and their current
        inventory levels.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        For small scale systems, or for state information that need not be kept
        for a long period of time, a set of system state beans may contain all the
        knowledge that the system ever has of these particular details.  Or, as is
        often the case, the system state beans will represent information that is
        stored permanently in some external database (such as a <code>CustomerBean</code> object
        that corresponds to a particular row in the CUSTOMERS table), and are
        created or removed from the server's memory as needed.  Entity Enterprise
        JavaBeans are also used for this purpose in large scale applications.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="2.5 Business Logic Beans" href="business_logic">
      
      <p>
        You should encapsulate the functional logic of your application as
        method calls on JavaBeans designed for this purpose.  These methods may
        be part of the same classes used for the system state beans, or they may
        be in separate classes dedicated to performing the logic.  In the latter
        case, you will usually need to pass the system state beans to be manipulated
        to these methods as arguments.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        For maximum code re-use, business logic beans should be designed and
        implemented so that they do <b>not</b> know they are being executed in a
        web application environment.  If you find yourself having to import a
        <code>javax.servlet.*</code> class in your bean, you
        are tying this business logic to the web application environment.  Consider
        rearranging things so that your <code>Action</code> classes (part of the
        Controller role, as described below) translate all required information
        from the HTTP request being processed into property setter calls on your
        business logic beans, after which a call to an <code>execute()</code> method
        can be made.  Such a business logic class can be reused in environments
        other than the web application for which they were initially constructed.
      </p>
        
      <p>
        Depending on the complexity and scope of your application, business logic
        beans might be ordinary JavaBeans that interact with system state beans
        passed as arguments, or ordinary JavaBeans that access a database using
        JDBC calls.  For larger applications, these beans will often be stateful
        or stateless Enterprise JavaBeans (EJBs) instead.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="2.6 Accessing Relational Databases" href="databases">
      
      <p>
        Struts can define the datasources for an application from within its standard 
        configuration file. A <b>simple</b> JDBC connection pool is also provided. See <a 
        href="building_controller.html#config">The Action Mappings Configuration File</a>
        section and the Utilities Developer Guide for details. 
      </p>
      <p>
        After the datasource is defined, here is an example of establishing a connection 
        from within a Action perform method.
      </p>
<pre>
public ActionForward
       perform(ActionMapping mapping,
               ActionForm form,
               HttpServletRequest request,
               HttpServletResponse response)
{
 try {
   javax.sql.DataSource dataSource =
     servlet.findDataSource(null);
   java.sql.Connection myConnection =
     dataSource.getConnection();

   //do what you wish with myConnection
 } catch (SQLException sqle) {
   getServlet().log("Connection.process", sqle);
 } finally {

   //enclose this in a finally block to make
   //sure the connection is closed
   try {
     myConnection.close();
   } catch (SQLException e) {
     getServlet().log("Connection.close", e);
   }
 }
}
</pre>
      
      <p>
        Note that the Struts generic connection pool is an <b>optional</b> component. Many 
        Struts applications use other connection pools for better performance, 
        especially with high-volume production systems. 
       </p>
      <p align="center">
        Next: <a href="building_view.html">Building View Components</a>
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  </body>
</document>
