<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="husted@apache.org">Ted Husted</author>
    <title>News and Status - Jakarta Struts</title>
  </properties>

<body>

    <section name="Status" href="status">

    <p>
        The <strong>stable production release</strong> is
        <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/binaries/">Struts 1.1.0</a> (29 June 2003).
    </p>

    <hr/>

    <ul>
    <li>
      See the <a href="../status.html">Development Roadmap</a> for an overview of future plans.
    </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/bugs.html">Apache Bug Database</a> for outstanding issues and
        enhancement requests.
      </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly/">Struts Nightly Build</a> for the
        latest development distribution.
    </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">Struts-Dev list</a> for current development
        communications.
    </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-struts/">Struts CVS</a> for the current development
        codebase.
      </li>
    <li>
       See the <a href="../releases.html">Release Guides</a> for our release process and coding conventions.
    </li>
    </ul>

    <hr/>

    <p>
        Struts is a completely open product. The <a href="../volunteers.html">Struts
        Committers</a> conduct all development business using the resources cited here, which are all available to the
        public.
        Only Struts Committers may write to the <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-struts/">CVS</a>.
        Developer contributions may be posted to <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/bugs.html">The Apache Bug
        Database</a>.
    </p>

    </section>

    <section name="Recent News" href="news">

<!--
<h4 id="a"> - </h4>
<p>
<a href=""></a>
</p>
<hr/>
-->

        <h4 id="a20031023">23 Oct 2003 - Struts IRC Channel: Quick, easy relief</h4>
        <p>
            The struts IRC channel at <code>irc.darkmyst.org #struts_users</code> was created
            for two reasons:
        </p>
        <p>
            1) To provide a place where struts questions can receive more
            interactive and immediate dialog.
        </p>
        <p>
            2) To relieve [OT] tensions from the list.
        </p>
        <p>
            Please feel free to visit the IRC channel to participate in either. It
            is good practice to keep the struts list clean from renegade threads.
        </p>
        <hr/>


        <h4 id="a20031021">21 Oct 2003 - Struts and JavaServer Faces talk by Craig McClanahan on Nov 5</h4>
        <p>
            The next meeting of the Silicon Valley Struts User BOF will be held at
            Netscape in Mountain View on Wednesday, November 5th. Craig McClanahan, a
            senior staff engineer for Sun Microsystems, will make a presentation on this
            topic:
        </p>
        <p>
            Struts and JavaServer Faces -- Competition or Coexistence?
        </p>
        <p>
            Craig is uniquely qualified to give this talk, because he is both the
            original creator of the Struts Framework and co-specification lead for
            JavaServer Faces (JSR-127). You will find the full announcement including
            directions to Netscape here:
        </p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.baychi.org/bof/struts/20031105a/">http://www.baychi.org/bof/struts/20031105a/</a>
            <br />
            (Please note the change of venue from VeriSign to Netscape for November)
        </p>
        <p>
            This meeting is being co-hosted by the Silicon Valley Java User Group
            (SVJUG) and the Java SIG of the East Bay I.T. Group (eBIG). Special thanks
            goes to SVJUG President Venki Seshaadri for arranging the meeting space at
            Netscape.
        </p>
        <p>
            The meeting is being recorded so that it can be made available online
            sometime following the presentation.
        </p>
        <hr/>


        <h4 id="a20031020">20 Oct 2003 - Struts Message Resource Doc</h4>
        <p>
            A short article detailing usage of the message resources functionality with Struts
            is avialable.  It seems like a lot of people are having problems with it, and this
            article may shed some light on this topic.
         </p>
        <p>
        You can find it at:
        <a href="http://www.systemmobile.com/articles/strutsMessageResources.html">
            http://www.systemmobile.com/articles/strutsMessageResources.html
        </a>
        </p>
        <hr/>

        <h4 id="a20031017">17 Oct 2003 - Spring Framework Integration Library for Struts</h4>
        <p>
            This project integrates the Spring Framework's Inversion of Control (IoC)
            into Struts 1.1+. It allows a Struts application to take advantage of IoC
            with little or no references to Spring. Now, instead of relying on
            singletons and static factories, Struts actions can have their
            dependencies automatically resolved.
        </p>

        <p>
            The integration uses Spring to create and populate Struts actions, using
            IoC to resolve dependencies. It does NOT use a custom request processor
            and therefore can be more easily used with existing web applications
            and/or other Struts extensions.
        </p>

        <p>
            To demonstrate the project, I modified the Struts-Example web app that is
            distributed with Struts 1.1 to use Spring to resolve all UserDatabase
            dependencies automatically. I invite any comments and suggestions.
        </p>

        <p>
            Website:  <a href="http://www.twdata.org/struts-spring">http://www.twdata.org/struts-spring</a>
        </p>
        <p>
           Download: <a href="http://www.twdata.org/struts-spring/struts-spring-0.1.zip">http://www.twdata.org/struts-spring/struts-spring-0.1.zip</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            Spring:   <a href="http://www.springframework.org">http://www.springframework.org</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            PS. This functionality adds under 100k to a Struts application
        </p>
        <hr/>

        <h4 id="a20031006">06 Oct 2003 - New Eclpse-based Struts Studio 5.0 - must see tool!</h4>
        <p>
            Here is a good new plugin for Eclipse specially designed for Struts and JSP development.
        </p>
        <p>
            Key Features:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>
              Based on Eclipse Development Platform.
            </li><li>
              Supports both Struts 1.1 (latest version) and Struts 1.0
            </li><li>
              Allows viewing and editing Struts configuration files using Web Flow, a tool for the visual development of Web applications using a drag-and- connect metaphor
              </li><li>
              Includes a built-in JSP editor with syntax highlighting, and two-way coordination with Web Flow
              </li><li>
              Includes a "one-click" library of Struts-specific tags in the built-in JSP editor
              </li><li>
              Allows editing in Web Flow before finishing JSP coding
              </li><li>
              Integrates with Tomcat Servlet engines for easy preview and running of Struts applications
              </li><li>
              Integrates with Ant for easy project control
              </li><li>
              Allows to import of pre-existing Struts projects into Exadel Struts Studio with intelligent auto-placement of the components in Web Flow and without any modifications required for the existing code
              </li><li>
              Includes a Code Wizard that automatically creates stub code for Action, FormBean, Forward, and Exception classes
              </li><li>
              Includes standard skeleton templates for new projects
              </li><li>
              Ability to edit templates for new code generation
              </li>
            </ul>
        <p>
        <a href="http://www.strutsstudio.com"><strong>www.strutsstudio.com</strong></a>
        </p>
        <hr/>

<p class="center">
<a href="news_2003_q3.html">
<strong>MORE NEWS</strong></a>
</p>

</section>


</body>
</document>
