<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="husted@apache.org">Ted Husted</author>
    <title>New and Status - Jakarta Struts</title>
  </properties>

<body>
<section name="Status" href="status">

<p>
The <b>stable production release</b> is <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/release/v1.0.2/">Struts 1.02</a> (11 February 2002).
</p>

<p>
<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/">Struts 1.1</a> is in its third <b>beta release</b> (30 December 2002).
</p>

<hr size="1" noshade=""/>

<ul>
<li>
  See the <a href="../status.html">Development Roadmap</a> for an overview of future plans.
</li>
<li>
  See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/bugs.html">Apache Bug Database</a> for outstanding issues and enhancement requests.
  </li>
<li>
  See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly/">Struts Nightly Build</a> for the latest development distribution.
</li>
<li>
  See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">Struts-Dev list</a> for current development communications.
  </li>
<li>
  See the <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-struts/">Struts CVS</a> for the current development codebase.
  </li>
</ul>

<hr size="1" noshade=""/>

<p>
Struts is a completely open product. The
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/volunteers.html">Struts Committers</a> conduct all development
business using the resources cited here, which are all available to the public. Only
Struts Committers may write to the
<a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-struts/">CVS</a>. Developer contributions may be posted
to <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/bugs.html">The Apache Bug Database</a>.
</p>

</section>

<section>
<p align="center"><a href="../faqs/helping.html#release">So when is the next release coming out?</a></p>
</section>

<section name="Community Support" href="community">

<p>
Download counts for Struts binary distributions in October 2002:
</p>

<pre>
  1.0.2:          15,780
  1.1-b1:            763
  1.1-b2:          9,695
  Nightlies:       2,961
                  ------
  Total:          29,199
                  ======
</pre>

<p>
or around 940 per day. That's second highest among Jakarta projects,
the highest being Tomcat with 80k-100k downloads per month.
</p>

<p>
These counts reflect only the main Apache website -- they don't count
any downloads from Apache mirrors, or from other sites that support
download of the Struts binaries, either by themselves or incorporated in
other tools. (The Apache Software License is wonderful for developers,
but terrible for bean counters ...)
</p>

<p>
As of November 14, the subscription counts to the Struts user mailing
lists (counting digest subscribers) is:
</p>

<pre>
  STRUTS-USER:     2,399
</pre>

<p>
which only just trails Tomcat:
</p>

<pre>
  TOMCAT-USER:     2,454
</pre>

</section>

<section name="Recent News" href="news">

<!--
<h3><a name=""></a> - </h3>
<p>
<a href=""></a>
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>
-->

    <h3><a name="20030211"></a>11 Feb 2003 - Scioworks Camino 3.0</h3>
    <p>
        Announcing Scioworks Camino 3.0, visual modelling tool for Jakarta Struts (v1.0 to v1.1-b3).
        For general information and list of new features, see
        <a href="">http://www.scioworks.net/servlets/ShowPage?pid=48&amp;dp=2</a>
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

    <h3><a name="20030206.1"></a>06 Feb 2003 - Expresso 5.0.3 Available for Download</h3>
    <p>
        [Side note:  As you may know, Version 4 of Expresso incorporated Struts for its
        MVC patterns and since then we have never looked back!
        Great job to the Struts development team!!!
        We will probably have Struts 1.1 integrated by the next .1 release (5.1)]
    </p>
    <p>
        The Expresso development team would like to announce the release of Expresso 5.0.3.
        Changes in this release include the introduction of the JSTL tag library and
        changes to allow full compatibility with JSTL's expression language.
    </p>
    <p>
        Bugfixes of note include better support for JNDI connections, initialization race
        condition fixes in the DBObject,
        and a SQL Injection fix in DBObject.searchAndRetrieve(String).
    </p>
    <p>
        For the last reason, it is recommended that all Expresso 5.0 users upgrade to 5.0.3 as soon as possible.
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>


    <h3><a name="20030206"></a>06 Feb 2003 -  Easy Struts 0.6.3 for Eclipse is out</h3>
    <p>
        Easy Struts 0.6.3 for Eclipse is now available.
        This release has no new features, only bug correction.
    </p>
    <p>
    <a href="http://easystruts.sf.net">http://easystruts.sf.net</a>
    </p>
    <p>
        Changes on 0.6.3<br/>
        * Fix root dir problem with Tomcat Sysdeo plugin<br/>
        * Fix roles generation in &lt;action.../><br/>
        * XML elements forward/form-property/exception/set-property respect DTD order
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

    <h3><a name="20030205"></a>05 Feb 2003 - Live Internet based Intermediate Struts Training by "Best Training"
        as voted by Java Developers Journal.</h3>

    <p>
    Live Internet based Intermediate Struts Training by "Best Training" as voted
    by Java Developers Journal. Learn good (best?) practices of web application
    development!
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    Multi row processing to DB
    </li>
    <li>
    Master/Detail processing
    </li>
    <li>
    Java Script Navigation
    </li>
    <li>
    and lots more, full agenda available, and it's all practical, no theory from me!
    </li>
    </ul>

    <p>
    The title of the class is "Pretenders vs. Pros" used to be Best and Worst
    Practices. This is version 3 of my intermediate advanced class.
    </p>

    <p>
    The class will meet online over 4 weeks, Saturdays at 10 AM Eastern on WebEx for
    about an hour or a bit more or less. My goal is to start on the 2/22.
    </p>

    <p>
    You should have a DSL or Cable connection, ( not sure how modem will work,
    Web Ex says yeah, I say nay. Maybe you can go to work on Saturday?), and the
    call in on a phone # to hear voice
    </p>

    <p>
    You will have a mail list and newsgroup to ask questions on, I expect a lot
    of questions on the labs.
    </p>

    <p>
    This is NOT a intro to MVC, it is suitable for people that did one
    Struts/MVC project or are very familiar with Servelts/JDBC/JSP/SQL. If you
    are a Struts experienced, this is the class for you! If you are new to Java
    / Web, this is not class for you. It help if you have production web/mvc
    experience.
    </p>

    <p>
    This is NOT for hands off types, it is lab based, for each hour of lecture,
    there is at least 8 hours of labs each week. I promise the labs will be
    challenging.
    </p>

    <p>
    If you can't or don't do the web labs, the next lesson will make no sense to
    you. Not doing "home work" labs, you will be invited not to attend the rest.
    I want to avoid pretenders, and nurturer pros.
    </p>

    <p>
    Scared?  The labs are doable. Clients like BEA, Borland, Cisco, IBM, etc.
    already did the hand on in person labs. That is how baseBeans.com got voted
    for "Best Training" by Java Developers Journal. I am willing to put it on
    the line! by teaching the class over the web via WebEx.com.  I really want
    to be the teach of the year next year as well!
    </p>

    <p>
    I also did Struts project recovery, and worked on 40,000 concurrent users
    Struts site, I guess I did more Struts training than all others combined,
    plus more.
    </p>

    <p>
    I am certified OO instructor, certified SQL performance and Tuning, J2EE
    certified and Java Certified by 3 different J2EE vendors! You will enjoy the
    class and learn, guranteed.
    </p>

    <p>
    You charges will be mostly for the WebEx + voice, so you can see my screen.
    When you register early, you will get a CD mailed to you with the lab
    materials. (International clients will have another way)
    </p>

    <p>
    If you register earlier, you get a cheaper price, goes up every few days,
    just like for seminars, the later your register, the more you pay.
    </p>

    <p>
    Since the cost is low, you can only register via the web, no P.O. or checks.
    </p>

    <p>
    To find the price, to discuss the class before hand, as well as lab
    questions later, etc. sign up at
    </p>

    <p>
    <a href="http://www.basebeans.net:8080/mailman/listinfo/mvc-programmers">
    http://www.basebeans.net:8080/mailman/listinfo/mvc-programmers
    </a>
    </p>

    <p>
    Please use the
    <a href="http://www.basebeans.net:8080/mailman/listinfo/mvc-programmers">
    MVC mail list</a>
    for any questions regarding this!
    </p>

    <p>
    </p>

    <p>
    Click here to register:
    <br/>
    <a href="http://www.basebeans.com/do/classReservation">http://www.basebeans.com/do/classReservation</a>
    </p>

    <p>
    The seminar is being given at near cost, on Open Source principles.
    </p>

    <p>
    Questions? Comments? On the
    <a href="http://www.basebeans.net:8080/mailman/listinfo/mvc-programmers">
    MVC mail list
    </a>.
    </p>

    <p>
    Vic Cekvenich &lt;<a href="mailto:vic@basebeans.com">vic@basebeans.com</a>&gt;
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>


    <h3><a name="20030204"></a>04 Feb 2003 - Struts Console v3.2</h3>
    <p>
    Struts Console version 3.2 is now available.<br />
    <a href=" http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/">http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/</a>
    </p>

    <p>
    Download Now: <br />
    http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/struts-console-3.2.zip
      -- OR --
    http://www.jamesholmes.com/struts/struts-console-3.2.tar.gz
    </p>

    <p>
        Struts Console is FREE software.
    </p>

    <p>
    This release fixes some bugs and adds a few small
    features.
    </p>

    <p>
        Changes with Struts Console v3.2
    </p>

    <ul>
        <li>
      Fixed bug where Page and Forward Pattern were not
         being displayed on the Controller screen for
         Struts 1.1 config files.
        </li>
        <li>
      Fixed bug where Form Bean add dialog would throw
         exceptions if a type was not entered.
        </li>
        <li>
      Fixed bug where Resource checkbox was not being
         properly set for &lt;field> elements in Validator
         config files.
        </li>
        <li>
      Fixed bug where Page Converter dialog was
         chopping off some of its tabs' contents.
        </li>
        <li>
      Fixed bug in Page Converter to properly convert
         &lt;img> tags.
        </li>
        <li>
      Added support for new "size" attribute of
         &lt;form-property> element.
         </li>
         <li>
      Added missing "indexListProperty" field for
         Validator config files.
         </li>
         <li>
      Added support for turning off config file
         validation in IDEA plugin.
         </li>
         <li>
     Removed "Debug" field from Controller screen for
         Struts 1.1 config files since it has been
         deprecated.
         </li>
         <li>
      Updated standalone version to preserve window
         size and location.
        </li>
    </ul>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>


    <h3><a name="20031701"></a>17 Jan 2003 - JSP taglibs + FreeMarker</h3>
    <p>
        The new 2.2 version of the FreeMarker template engine now natively supports JSP tag libraries.
        The first preview release of the new version is downloadable from the project home page at
    </p>
    <p>
      <a href="http://freemarker.sourceforge.net">http://freemarker.sourceforge.net</a>
    </p>
    <p>
        This new ability is of special significance to Jakarta Struts and Taglib
        communities, since you are no longer forced into a tradeoff. Before now, you
        had to make a choice: either you couldn't use a template engine, or you
        couldn't use the taglibs. With FreeMarker, you no longer need to abandon any
        of the valuable taglibs you came to know and love if you want to change your
        view technology from JSP to a template engine.
    </p>

    <p>
        Aside from the native JSP taglib support, FreeMarker 2.2 introduces many new
        improvements in areas of macro handling, namespaces, automatic escaping of
        interpolations and whitespace handling.
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

    <h3><a name="20030118"></a>18 Jan 2003 - Struts Training in DC and NYC</h3>
    <p>
        Increase Your Struts Productivity - Attend the BaseBeans Public Struts
        Training!!!!
    </p>
    <p>
        We have a 11 hour public class in DC and in NYC in January.
    </p>
    <p>
        Washington DC Class -- January 18th 2003
        NYC Class  -- January 24th 2003
    </p>
    <p>
        This class is taught by baseBeans Engineering, the company voted to have the
        best hands on training class by JDJ for their "Fast Track to Struts" class.
    </p>
    <p>
        Get your training from the #1 trainer with a money back guarantee!!!!
    </p>
    <p>
        You will pay $50 to register and be billed the balance. Upon registration,
        you will be shipped a CD that contains the tools needed for the class, such
        as an IDE, App. Server, some sample working source code, Struts, etc.
    </p>
    <p>
        Follow this link to register:  http://www.basebeans.com/do/classReservation
    </p>
    <p>
        At the training, we will cover Struts, Java Server Faces, JDO, DAO,
        JDBC,etc.
    </p>
    <p>
        A pre-requisite for attendance is some Struts knowledge or at least Servlet
        and SQL knowledge. This class is targeted at tech leads. Bring your
        questions and receive practical advice from the baseBeans team.
    </p>
    <p>
        You can FedEx a check or a PO for the balance to BaseBeans.
    </p>
    <p>
        Prior paid students and clients are free for this class, as always, but we
        need to know you are coming.
    </p>
    <p>
        Hope to see you there,
    </p>
    <p>
    #1. We are looking for more people to develop basicPortal.sf.net (baseBeans.com is on basicPortal).
        Now we are working on setup.exe (currently in beta but available) that will install DB,
        Tomcat (because people do not know how to set up JDBC realms in server.xml).
        As you know bP demos master detail processing, XML, RSS, CMS, task tracking, contact management,
        JDBC realms, BLOBs, CRUD,  JMeter, JaserReports, etc.
        Just e-mail me if you know Struts and want to contribute to open source.
    </p>
    <p>
    #2. Bring a laptop to public training in DC/NYC training to get *FREE* autographed "Struts in Action".
        Prices goes up tmrw by 9:30 AM Eastern.
        This is not intro to Struts, you must know some MVC (and JAVA and SQL well),
        I do not like teaching intro.
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

    <h3><a name="20030106"></a>06 Jan 2003 - neteye actioncache 1.1</h3>
    <p>
        The neteye actioncache is a Struts extension that caches the result of
        actions and views. It can boost the performance of your website because
        time expensive operations like data retrieval, JSP processing or XSLT
        transformations are only performed when needed.
    </p>
    <p>
        The new release now uses the Struts 1.1 Plugin and RequestProcessor
        interfaces to handle request.
    </p>
    <p>
        Sources and documentation can be found at
        <a href="http://actioncache.neteye.de">http://actioncache.neteye.de</a>
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

    <h3><a name=""></a>4 Jan 2003 - JBoss Handbook</h3>
    <p>
        I am pleased to announce the availability of the book
        "JBoss 3.0 Deployment and Administration Handbook".
        The book provides a comprehensive coverage of the JBoss 3.0 server, focusing on
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
        JBoss architecture
        </li>
        <li>
        Deploying and configuring EJBs, web applications, EAR files, JCA resource adapters, JMX MBeans etc on JBoss
        </li>
        <li>
        JBoss CMP 2.0 features
        </li>
        <li>
        JBoss clustering
        </li>
        <li>
        Configuring JMS and JCA
        </li>
        <li>
        Configuring security, logging, JavaMail
        </li>
        <li>
        JBoss custom features like scheduling
        </li>
        <li>
        Administration and monitoring of the server.
        </li>
   </ul>

    <p>
        The book will be a valuable resource for anyone using JBoss in production and development.
        The book is published by WROX Press and is available on
        <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ISBN=1861008120/hitchhikeguidetoA/">
        Amazon</a> [ISBN # 1861008120].
    </p>
    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>


<p align="center">
<a href="news_2002_q4.html">
<b>MORE NEWS</b></a>
</p>

</section>


</body>
</document>
