<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="husted@apache.org">Ted Husted</author>
    <title>News and Status - Jakarta Struts</title>
  </properties>

<body>

    <section name="Status" href="status">

    <p>
        The <strong>stable production release</strong> is
        <a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/binaries/">Struts 1.1.0</a> (29 June 2003).
    </p>

    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

    <ul>
    <li>
      See the <a href="../status.html">Development Roadmap</a> for an overview of future plans.
    </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/bugs.html">Apache Bug Database</a> for outstanding issues and
        enhancement requests.
      </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly/">Struts Nightly Build</a> for the
        latest development distribution.
    </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">Struts-Dev list</a> for current development
        communications.
    </li>
    <li>
        See the <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-struts/">Struts CVS</a> for the current development
        codebase.
      </li>
    <li>
       See the <a href="../releases.html">Release Guides</a> for our release process and coding conventions.
    </li>
    </ul>

    <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

    <p>
        Struts is a completely open product. The <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/volunteers.html">Struts
        Committers</a> conduct all development business using the resources cited here, which are all available to the
        public.
        Only Struts Committers may write to the <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs/jakarta-struts/">CVS</a>.
        Developer contributions may be posted to <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/bugs.html">The Apache Bug
        Database</a>.
    </p>

    </section>

    <section name="Recent News" href="news">

<!--
<h3><a name=""></a> - </h3>
<p>
<a href=""></a>
</p>
<hr size="1" noshade=""/>
-->

        <h3><a name="20030829"></a>29 Aug 2003 - Core J2EE Patterns -- Expanded and Updated in Second Edition</h3>
        <p>
            From the Back Cover:
        </p>
        <p>
            <i>"The authors do a great job describing useful patterns for application architectures.
            The section on refactoring is worth the price of the entire book!"</i> <br />
            --Craig McClanahan, Struts Founder and Specification Lead for JavaServer Faces
        </p>
        <p>
            Developers often confuse learning the technology with learning to design with the technology.
            In this book, senior architects from the Sun Java Center share their cumulative design experience on Java 2
            Platform, Enterprise Edition (J2EE) technology.
        </p>
        <p>
            The primary focus of the book is on patterns, best practices, design strategies, and proven solutions using
            the key J2EE technologies including JavaServer Pages (JSP), Servlets, Enterprise JavaBeans (EJB), and Java
            Message Service (JMS) APIs.
            The J2EE Pattern Catalog with 21 patterns and numerous strategies is presented to document and promote best
            practices for these technologies.
        </p>
        <p>
            Core J2EE Patterns, Second Edition offers the following:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>J2EE Pattern Catalog with 21 patterns--fully revised and newly documented patterns providing proven
                solutions for enterprise applications</li>
            <li>Design strategies for the presentation tier, business tier, and integration tier</li>
            <li>Coverage of servlets, JSP, EJB, JMS, and Web Services</li>
            <li>J2EE technology bad practices</li>
            <li>Refactorings to improve existing designs using patterns</li>
            <li>Fully illustrated with UML diagrams</li>
            <li>Extensive sample code for patterns, strategies, and refactorings</li>
         </ul>
        <p>
            Find links to <b>Core J2EE Patterns</b> and other great books in the
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/resources/related_books.html">Struts Resource section</a>.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name=""></a>28 Aug 2003 - Commons Validator 1.1.0 Alpha is now available for testing</h3>
        <p>
            Please refer to <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/validator/tasks.html">
                http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/validator/tasks.html</a>
            that details some of the changes that have taken place since the 1.0.2 release.
        </p>
        <p>
            Downloads: <br />
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/~rleland/ValidatorAlpha/">
                http://jakarta.apache.org/~rleland/ValidatorAlpha/</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            Just a reminder: <br />
            The release process is following the same general procedures established for the
            <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/dev/release.html">Apache HTTPD project</a> and
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/releases/">Jakarta Commons products</a>, and utilize the HTTPD
            numbering scheme.
            The release will initially be given an Alpha status and made available through the Release Manager's home
            directory.
            Pursuant to a Majority Vote on the /commons-dev/ Mailing List, the release may be moved to the public
            release directory.
            The vote may also serve to reclassify the release to be of *Beta* or *General Availability* (GA) quality,
            as defined by the Apache HTTPD project.
            Subsequent votes may reclassify the release, either to promote it or to demote it, as need be.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name="20030828"></a> - ASF Protest Euopean Software Patentability Rule Changes</h3>
        <p>
            On September 1st the European Commission is going to vote a revised version of the European Patentability
            rules.
            The proposed revision contains a set of serious challenges to Open Source development since regulation
            regarding software patents will be broadly extended and might forbid independent development of innovative
            (Open Source and not) software-based solutions.
        </p>
        <p>
            The European Open Source community is very concerned about the upcoming new regulation and has organized a
            demo protest for August 27, asking Open Source supporting sites to change their home pages to let everyone
            know what is going on at the European Parliament.
            The Apache Software Foundation supports this initiative.
            To show its support, a protest announcement is being displayed on all top-level home pages from
            Aug 28 through Sep 1.
        </p>
        <p>
            For further information please see <a href="http://swpat.ffii.org">http://swpat.ffii.org</a> and
            <a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org">http://petition.eurolinux.org</a>.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>


        <h3><a name="20030825"></a>25 Aug 2003 - Model-driven Development for Struts/EJB</h3>
        <p>
        Alpharetta, GA - Metanology releases new Model-driven Development Environment (MDE) products
        </p>
        <p>
        Overview:<br />
        MDE is a full featured, model-driven development environment that includes a
        UML modeler and MetaProgramTM editor that integrates with a Java IDE.  MDE
        transforms a simple UML model of an application into the majority of the
        implementation by executing MetaPrograms. Applications are completed using
        traditional development techniques.
        MDE for EJB and MDE for J2EE enhance the company's existing MDE for Struts.
        MDE for EJB creates session beans, entity beans, message driven beans,
        business objects and value objects from simple UML models. MDE for J2EE
        enhances MDE for Struts and MDE for EJB by interfacing the Struts user
        interface to EJB services.
        </p>
        <p>
        Platform Independent Modeling Typical modeling techniques require a class
        for each element in the implementation resulting in complex models that are
        difficult to understand and maintain. MDE promotes modeling what the
        application does, not how it is built, making modeling fast, easy, and
        reusable across platforms.
        </p>
        <p>
        MetaPrograms A combination of Java and JSP-style syntax, MetaPrograms are
        easy to write, contain all the technical details of architecture, and create
        multiple files in the implementation from a single class in the model.
        MetaProgramming with MDE gives you complete control of how the model is
        turned into code.  Rather than writing all the code by hand, MetaProgramming
        let's you "write the code that writes the code."TM
        </p>
        <p>
        MDE Life Cycle Life cycle benefits are two fold. First, life cycle tools
        preserve your hand-written code from one generation to the next. Second,
        they replace existing MetaProgram generated code with updated MetaProgram
        code. Used to its fullest, MDE is ideal for iterative and incremental
        development methods, Agile and Extreme Programming.
        </p>
        <p>
        Learn more and download a free evaluation at <a href="http://www.metanology.com">"www.metanology.com</a>.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name="20030820"></a>20 Aug 2003 - Introduction to Hibernate presentation</h3>
        <p>
        Introduction to Hibernate by Norman Klein:<br />
        6:30 pm on September 3rd in Mountain View
        </p>
        <p>
            The next meeting of the Silicon Valley Struts User BOF is scheduled to take
            place at VeriSign in Mountain View on Wednesday, September 3rd. You must
            arrive between 6:30 and 7:00pm to register with VeriSign security as a
            guest. Norman Klein, an independent software consultant, will present an
            introduction to Hibernate. Hibernate is an open source data persistence
            framework. Please refer to the online announcement for the details and
            directions to the meeting site:
        </p>
        <p>
              <a href="http://www.baychi.org/bof/struts/20030903/">http://www.baychi.org/bof/struts/20030903/</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            It is important that I get an accurate headcount in advance for meeting
            facility planning purposes. So, please RSVP for the meeting by sending an
            email to me with "Struts User September Meeting" as the subject.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name="20030730"></a>30 Jul 2003 - StrutsDoc 0.3.1 Released</h3>
        <p>
            StrutsDoc 0.3.1 has been released and can be found here:
        </p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=49385">
                http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=49385</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            This release fixes a few minor bugs and includes a Spanish translation of the user guide.
        </p>
        <p>
            The strutsdoc for the struts-example application has been updated and can be found at:
        </p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.systemmobile.com/strutsdoc/struts-example">
                http://www.systemmobile.com/strutsdoc/struts-example</a>
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name=""></a>27 Jul 2003 - Log4J Administration Webapp built with struts</h3>
        <p>
            Just thought I'd let you know that LogWeb, a fully functional administration interface for Log4J,
            has been implemented with Struts.
        </p>
        <p>
            LogWeb is freely available at:
        </p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.codeczar.com/projects/logweb/index.html">
                http://www.codeczar.com/projects/logweb/index.html</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            Thanks to the struts team. Without struts, LogWeb would have taken much longer to develop.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name=""></a>24 Jul 2003 - brief example using iBATIS from Struts</h3>
        <p>
            There are often newbie requests asking how to deal with a database layer
            from Struts. Since there are so many ways this can be done,
            'simple' examples of how this can be done seem hard to come by. Since I
            currently use iBATIS as my persistence mechanism of choice, I created a
            simple Struts application demonstrating just one way a developer could
            use database persistence:
        </p>
        <p>
            <a href="http://www.reumann.net/do/struts/ibatisLesson1">http://www.reumann.net/do/struts/ibatisLesson1</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            I didn't really have the time to write up a full lesson like the others
            on the site, but I did provide some comments on a few of the components
            that deal directly with iBATIS http://www.ibatis.com/.(The iBATIS
            documentation is excellent and should be read first along side the
            application). I've looked at the way others have plugged into the
            database layer and happen to think the approach I demonstrate is simple
            yet also very flexible.
        </p>
        <p>
            For a more powerful implementation the user should check out the
            awesome JPetStore application at
            <a href="http://www.ibatis.com/jpetstore/jpetstore.html">http://www.ibatis.com/jpetstore/jpetstore.html</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            Also, Vic has an interesting approach using iBATIS demonstrated in
            the basicPortal application that you can check out
            here: <a href="http://www.basicportal.com/">http://www.basicportal.com/</a>
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name="20030717"></a>17 Jul 2003 - Velocity Tools 1.0 released</h3>
        <p>
            The Velocity team is happy to announce the release of Velocity Tools 1.0.
        </p>
        <p>
            Velocity Tools is a collection of Velocity subprojects offering servlets and
            tools for rapid, clean web development with Velocity, tools for using Velocity
            with Struts, and a set of generic tools to help with any Velocity project.
        </p>
        <p>
            Please see the Velocity Tools website
            (<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/tools/index.html">
                http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/tools/index.html</a>) for more information.
        </p>
        <p>
            For more info on Velocity+Struts see
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/tools/struts/index.html">
                http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/tools/struts/index.html</a>
        </p>
        <p>
            Both source (<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/sourceindex.cgi">
            http://jakarta.apache.org/site/sourceindex.cgi</a>) and binary
            (<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/binindex.cgi">http://jakarta.apache.org/site/binindex.cgi</a>)
            distributions are availablethrough the the usual Apache mirror sites.
            Please remember to verify the signatures of the distribution using the keys found on the main Apache web
            site (<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/velocity-tools/KEYS">
            http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/velocity-tools/KEYS</a>) when downloading from a mirror.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name="20030714"></a>14 Jul 2003 - Struts updated in Out-of-the-Box 2.1 release</h3>
        <p>
            Struts 1.1 is included in Out-of-the-Box 2.1, an intelligent distribution of over 100 Open Source projects
            for Java developers on both Linux and Windows.
        </p>
        <p>
            Major changes since Out-of-the-Box 2.0:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>Added Oracle and DB2 integration for JBoss and the sample projects</li>
            <li>Semi-automatic database switching for JBoss and the samples after installation</li>
            <li>Support for Red Hat, SuSE, and Mandrake Linux (in addition to Windows XP/2000)</li>
            <li>Added PHP, phpMyAdmin, and phpBB for LAMP developers</li>
            <li>Dozens of project updates, including Struts, JBoss, Hibernate, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Eclipse, and
              more</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
            The free Community Edition is fully functional, does not expire, and does
            not require registration.  It installs just over 25 of the 100+ projects,
            including JBoss, MySQL, and Castor, and comes with the Castor sample project
            and nearly all of the Enterprise Edition documentation.
        </p>
        <p>
            Please visit <a href="http://www.ejbsolutions.com">http://www.ejbsolutions.com</a> for details or to
            download the free Community Edition.
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name="20030711"></a>11 Jul 2003 - new release of bP</h3>
        <p>
            A new build of bP Jasic v9.7_3 was released. bP is a Struts CMS app, that requires a DB to run.
        </p>
        <p>
            It uses JSTL 1.1 (not 1.03), which requires JSP 2.0 (Tomcat 5 AND Resin 3 included).
        </p>
        <p>
            Also three are few new newsgroups added to new.baseBeans.com (new: Oracle, MS SQL, C#, old are JDO,
            Eclipse, JavaScript, etc.) so refresh your news reader if you are using news.basebeans.com
        </p>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

        <h3><a name=""></a>09 Jul 2003 - Struts Studio Professional</h3>
        <p>
            Building on the tremendous success of the first release of Struts Studio and incorporating substantial
            feedback from the Struts community, Exadel, Inc. has now unveiled a powerful new Web Integrated Development
            Environment (WIDE) for Jakarta Struts:
        </p>
        <p>
            Struts Studio Professional
        </p>
        <p>
            Struts Studio Professional is available now for download and purchase from
            <a href="http://www.exadel.com/products_strutsstudio_professional.htm">
                http://www.exadel.com/products_strutsstudio_professional.htm</a>.
            To read more about Struts Studio see <a href="http://www.StrutsStudio.com">http://www.StrutsStudio.com</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
            New features.
        </p>
        <p>
            In addition to full support for Struts 1.0, this new tool from Exadel also supports all of the features of
            the recently announced 1.1 release of Jakarta Struts, including:
        </p>
        <ul>
            <li>Tiles - a new "template-based" page authoring framework</li>
            <li>Validation Framework - a "rule-based" engine for validation of user input</li>
            <li>Modules - special framework for multi-modular web applications</li>
            <li>Support for the use of arbitrary tag libraries</li>
            <li>Ability to print Web Flow diagram with zooming</li>
            <li>And many others...</li>
         </ul>
        <hr size="1" noshade=""/>

<p align="center">
<a href="news_2003_q2.html">
<b>MORE NEWS</b></a>
</p>

</section>


</body>
</document>
