<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="husted@apache.org">Ted Husted</author>
    <title>New and Status - Jakarta Struts</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="News" href="news">

    <!--
    <h4 id=""> - </h4>
      <p>
    <a href=""></a>
    </p>
    <hr/>
    -->

     <h4 id="S20030630">30 Jun 2003 - Struts 1.1 Final released</h4>
     <p>
         The Struts team is proud, and extremely pleased, to announce the Final
         release of Struts 1.1. This release includes significant new
         functionality, as well as numerous fixes for bugs which were reported
         against the previous release, and supersedes the earlier 1.0.2 version
         as the latest official release of Struts from the Apache Software
         Foundation.
     </p>
     <p>The binary distribution is available at: <a href=
     "http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/binaries/">
     http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/binaries/</a> </p>
     <p>and the source distribution is available at: <a href=
     "http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/source/">
     http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/source/</a></p>
     <p>In addition, the library distribution, which contains updated binaries
        without the sample applications, is available at: </p>
     <p><a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/library/">
     http://www.apache.org/dist/jakarta/struts/library/</a> </p>
     <p>Details of the changes in this release are available in the Release
     Notes,which can be found here: </p>
     <p><a href=
     "http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/userGuide/release-notes-1.1.html">
     http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/userGuide/release-notes-1.1.html</a> </p>
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030624">24 Jun 2003 - JPlates 2.1 is available - great
     alternative to JSP for Struts</h4>
 
     <p>I know you're all busy with your current projects, but maybe the next
        one will be much easier if you use JPlates. </p>
     <p>JPlates 2.1 is now available for licensed use and evaluation. JPlates
        is a fully object-oriented template-processing system that combines
        many of
        the best features of Java with great template processing features to
        create
        a terrific alternate to JSP for use    with Struts. </p>
     <p>JPlates generates true JVM classes that are seamlessly compatible with
        Java, and every JPlates method is an executable template. What that
        means is
        that you can build your MVC views using objects and classes and methods
        (and
        not includes), just    like you build everything else. </p>
     <p>Take a look at
        <a href="http://www.jplates.com/">http://www.jplates.com/</a>,
        and please follow the link on the left side to the note about JSP
        scriptlets. </p>
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030617">17 Jun 2003 - Eclipse begins new webtools project</h4>
     <p>I know this list contains a wealth of production minded talent. So, I
        wanted to let everyone know that eclipse.org has begun discussions on a
        new
        project to create a webtools platform for developing J2EE projects
        under the
        Eclipse IDE. It is currently open to discussion on the webtools list.
        So, if
        you want to donate    some talent and/or ideas ... go to
        <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/webtools/index.html">
        http://www.eclipse.org/webtools/index.html</a>. </p>
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030611">11 Jun 2003 - Last chance to register for online web
     training for advancedStruts.</h4>
     <p>Advanced Struts best practices web cast training by winner of best
     training
        with money back guarantee (this is no *Intro* To    Struts): </p>
     <p>Last chance to Register now by going to www.baseBeans.com and click
     training,
        then click register. The cost is very reasonable and cost effective
        take web
        training, compared to a conference cost. The rate goes up a lot as we
        get closer
        to the start date to $300+; register today for $180. Training starts in
        a few
        weeks, right after JavaOne; on 6/21. We will meet every Saturday for 3
        Saturdays
        via a web cast (DSL/Cable recommended) at 10AM Eastern (NYC) Time to
        complete
        the labs. Outstanding reviews/references. If you can't get private
        training
        paid by your company, this is it, (and over the web!-ask voice
        questions via
        webcast!) </p>
     <p>Best training hands on labs, voted by Java Developers Journal (search
        for Training) </p>
     <p>We offer money back guarantee, take the classes; you must do the labs,
        and after you watch all the sessions, ask for money back if you do not
        think
        it was valuable! If you know Struts. This WILL    make you a better
        programmer. </p>
     <p>Shortly after you register, you will receive the training materials, a
        book and the labs. </p>
     <p>We will write an application from scratch in Struts with DB access,
     updates,
        master detail processing, validation, navigation, tiles, JSTL, testing,
        reporting,
        mail, etc. We will cover good practices and bad. Full agenda to follow
        on the
        mail list (sign up    for mail list on the main page of baseBeans.com).
        </p>
     <p>Students are always able to retake future training for FREE (even live
           in person training offered in the big north east    cities) </p>
     <p>Struts Instructors: If you want to teach Advanced Struts in the future
           with baseBeans materials, you must sit trough a class by    Vic! </p
           >
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030608">08 Jun 2003 - Wildcard-Matched    Actions</h4>
     <p>This project allows wildcards to be used in Struts 1.1+ action
     mappings.
        The wildcard-matched values can then be substituted in the values of
        various
        Struts action mapping and action forward attributes. It uses the
        wildcard matching
        class from Apache Cocoon which is the default matching class used to
        match
        XML transformation pipelines.</p>
     <p>The bottom line of this project is you can write generic actions that
        can be used to match multiple actions. Even the "type" attribute which
        specifies the Action class can have wildcard-matched values
        substituted to match multiple Action classes for one action mapping. It
        also
        works great for Struts applications that use DispatchActions or other
        generic
        Actions. </p>
     <p>For example:</p>
 <pre><code>
               &lt;action    path="/edit*"
                          type="org.twdata.struts.ScriptAction"
                     attribute="{1}Form"
                         scope="request"
                      validate="false"
                     parameter="/WEB-INF/scripts/Edit{1}.bsh"&gt;
 
                   &lt;forward name="failure" path="/mainMenu.jsp"/&gt;
                   &lt;forward name="success" path="/{1}.jsp"/&gt;
               &lt;/action&gt;
 </code></pre>
 
     <p>Project page:
        <a href="http://www.twdata.org/struts-wildcard/">
        http://www.twdata.org/struts-wildcard/</a> </p>
     <p>Comments and suggestions always welcome. </p>
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030604">04 Jun 2003 - Updated Struts-Faces Integration Library
     </h4>
     <p>As you might already be aware, the Public Draft 2 version of the
     JavaServer
        Faces specification is now available: </p>
     <p>
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaserverfaces/download.html">
        http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaserverfaces/download.html</a> </p>
     <p>with many new and exciting features. The EA4 version of the JavaServer
        Faces reference implementation is available as part of the Java Web
        Services
        Developer Pack 1.2 release (and easily    separable for use on other
        containers): </p>
     <p>
     <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/downloads/webservicespack.html">
     http://java.sun.com/webservices/downloads/webservicespack.html</a> </p>
     <p>This release of the Struts-Faces integration library has been updated
           to accomodate the API changes in the new version. Nightly builds of
           the updated
           code, starting with the 20030605 version    (i.e. tonight) will be
           available at: </p>
     <p>
        <a href=
        "http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly/struts-faces/"
        >http://jakarta.apache.org/builds/jakarta-struts/nightly/struts-faces/
        </a> </p>
     <p>(Versions up through and including 20030604 are for the EA3 release of
        Faces.)</p>
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030527.1">27 May 2003 - new release of bP</h4>
     <p>basicPortal is an open source Portal app that stores content via DB
     access,
           a sample Struts v.1 webapp. It is built on scaffoldingXPress,
           commercially
           supported, with JSTL and DAO. Both    are available on <a
                 href="http://basicportal.sf.net/">http://basicportal.sf.net/
                 </a> </p>
     <p>New release (v095) includes a video demo sample, includes Tomcat (in
     addition
           to Resin), reporting (helper based on Jasper), includes stress test,
           async
           operations, options collection example    and misc. fixes. </p>
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030527">27 May 2003 - Barracuda 1.2.0    Released!</h4>
     <p>The long awaited stable release of Barracuda 1.2.0 is finally    here!
     </p>
     <p>You can download it at:
        <a href="http://barracudamvc.org/downloads/">
        http://barracudamvc.org/downloads/</a> </p>
     <p>A lot has changed since the 1.1.1 release. Barracuda moved to
        <a
        href="http://www.barracudamvc.org/">http://www.barracudamvc.org/</a>,
        the source has been refactored, there now exist two contrib packages
        with reusable
        code and example webapps to show off their functionality, numerous bugs
        have
        been fixed, quite a few new features have been added and many features
        improved,
        and deployment of Barracuda and BarracudaDiscRack is now incredibly
        simplified. </p>
     <p>See the most important changes here... <br />
        <a href=
        "http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/docs/changes.html#1_2_0_Release_Note
        s">
        http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/docs/changes.html#1_2_0_Release_Notes
        </a> and
        here...
        <a href="http://barracudamvc.org/BarracudaDiscRack/docs/changes.html">
        http://barracudamvc.org/BarracudaDiscRack/docs/changes.html</a> </p>
     <p>For a more detailed explanation of the changes, see.... <br />
        <a href=
        "http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/javadocs/org/enhydra/barracuda/A_Cha
        nges_H">
        http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/javadocs/org/enhydra/barracuda/A_Chan
        ges_H</a> </p>
     <p>For information on building and deploying Barracuda, see... <br />
        <a href="http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/docs/build_deploy.html">
        http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/docs/build_deploy.html</a> </p>
     <p>And, of course, don't forget to try out the new contrib apps.    See...
     <br />
        <a href="http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/docs/contrib_package.html">
        http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/docs/contrib_package.html</a> </p>
     <p>All this information, and more, is available at: <br />
        <a href="http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/index.html">
        http://barracudamvc.org/Barracuda/index.html</a> <br />
        and here... <br />
        <a href="http://barracudamvc.org/BarracudaDiscRack/docs/index.html">
        http://barracudamvc.org/BarracudaDiscRack/docs/index.html</a> </p>
     <p>Thanks to everyone on the BarraucdaMVC team for all your hard work and
        thanks to all the users who continue to utilize this great project! Oh,
        and
        special thanks to those who donated hosting, time, money, and effort to
        make
        barracudamvc.org    possible. <br />
        <a href="http://www.visi.com/~hoju/barracuda/donations.html">
        http://www.visi.com/~hoju/barracuda/donations.html</a> </p>
     <hr/>
 
 
     <h4 id="S20030404">04 Apr 2003 - Struts Action    Scripting</h4>
     <p>Struts Action Scripting is a Struts plug-in that allows development of
        Struts actions using the power and simplicity of any favorite scripting
        language.
        This plug-in to the Struts Framework provides the ScriptedAction, a
        Struts
        Action class that, using BSF (Bean Scripting Framework), enables Struts
        developers
        to create Struts Actions in the language of their choice. Supported
        languages
        include JavaScript, Python, TCL, ActiveScript,    PerlScript, and
        others </p>
     <p><a href="http://alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/strutsscripting">
     http://alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/strutsscripting</a> </p>
     <hr/>
 
    <p class="center">
        <a href="news_2003_q1.html">
    <strong>MORE NEWS</strong></a>
    </p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
